<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>/dev/isra/blog/* - microservices</title><link href="//iffm.me/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="//127.0.0.1:8000/feeds/microservices.tag.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>//iffm.me/</id><updated>2018-05-10T00:00:00+04:00</updated><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title>Choreography and Orchestration</title><link href="//iffm.me/choreography-and-orchestration.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-05-10T00:00:00+04:00</published><updated>2018-05-10T00:00:00+04:00</updated><author><name>Israel Fermín Montilla</name></author><id>tag:iffm.me,2018-05-10:/choreography-and-orchestration.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;On a &lt;a href="http://iffm.me/my-take-on-microservices.html"&gt;previous article&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;em&gt;microservices&lt;/em&gt;, we went through the best practices I've seen,
which doesn't mean those are the only ones, it only means that those are the ones I've seen work for me
and the ones I've tried.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time, I would like to focus on &lt;strong&gt;Choreography over …&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On a &lt;a href="http://iffm.me/my-take-on-microservices.html"&gt;previous article&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;em&gt;microservices&lt;/em&gt;, we went through the best practices I've seen,
which doesn't mean those are the only ones, it only means that those are the ones I've seen work for me
and the ones I've tried.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time, I would like to focus on &lt;strong&gt;Choreography over Orchestration&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Rely on data, not services&lt;/strong&gt; because
I feel I didn't develop enough on these ones and those are really important these are also the two &lt;em&gt;principles&lt;/em&gt; 
that will help you &lt;em&gt;avoid sync calls&lt;/em&gt;, which is usually a good practice for inter-service communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But first:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Internal &lt;em&gt;REST&lt;/em&gt; services, why not?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't get me wrong, I love &lt;em&gt;REST&lt;/em&gt;, I like building &lt;em&gt;API&lt;/em&gt;s and I enjoy using a well designed one for sure, but for internal
communication I prefer to avoid it unless the communication &lt;strong&gt;needs&lt;/strong&gt; to be synchronous, there are some cases where you can't
help it and it's not always because of a bad design, sometimes the use case itself enforces that restriction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you find yourself using network calls most of the time, something will most likely go wrong. Network is not 100% reliable
and, &lt;strong&gt;always&lt;/strong&gt; remember, &lt;em&gt;if something can fail, it will fail&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Increases overall response time&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take a look at the following figure: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Services map" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/s/k261ik209fporvr/service_down.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Response times are not taking into account the wait time while the downstream services
respond. This means, &lt;em&gt;service 1&lt;/em&gt; queries &lt;em&gt;service 2&lt;/em&gt;, it does &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; and takes 10ms to respond. Also, &lt;em&gt;Service 1&lt;/em&gt; queries
&lt;em&gt;Service 3&lt;/em&gt; which queries &lt;em&gt;Service 4&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Service 5&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Service 4&lt;/em&gt; does &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; and takes 300ms to respond and &lt;em&gt;Service 5&lt;/em&gt;
queries &lt;em&gt;Service 6&lt;/em&gt; which takes 1000ms to respond, then &lt;em&gt;Service 5&lt;/em&gt; does &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; and takes another 1200ms to come back to
&lt;em&gt;Service 3&lt;/em&gt;, which has been waiting 2200ms to get all the data it needs to do &lt;em&gt;some stuff&lt;/em&gt; which takes 300ms. By this time,
&lt;em&gt;Service 1&lt;/em&gt; has been waiting 2500ms for all the data it needs to do a 120ms &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; and return back to the upstream caller,
which could be another service waiting or the end user. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that the above flow paralelizes all the needed downstream calls per service, so in this case, the total response time will be
constrained by the slowest call chain. If you were using a stack where doing multiprocessing or async programming is not an easy
option, you'll have to add up the response time for all of the downstream calls because in reality the service in question
is being blocked while waiting for the network call to finish and, only then, making the second call and blocking until it comes back
and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several ways you can keep the same setup, you can add several levels of cache in between services, you can add a timeout
to the network calls but everything comes at a cost. If you're keeping a synchronous approach to answer certain questions it's because
you need your data as fresh as possible, so, the more cache you add the more stale your data could be. You could also add a timeout to
your calls but, if one of them times out, you'll fail in responding to the upstream caller and it will look like the system is down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What if someone is down?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let imagine &lt;em&gt;Service 6&lt;/em&gt; is down because we had a buggy release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means, &lt;em&gt;Service 1&lt;/em&gt; will have to wait 1500ms before returning an error upstream, you can mitigate this
with a &lt;a href="https://www.martinfowler.com/bliki/CircuitBreaker.html"&gt;circuit breaker&lt;/a&gt; approach or returning a 
cached response for the query you're trying to answer but,
again, unless you really need this to be synchronous, you'd be adding more complexity to an already complex
system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, what if it isn't a &lt;em&gt;read&lt;/em&gt; operation, what if we're actually &lt;em&gt;writing&lt;/em&gt; downstream and the last write fails
because of &lt;em&gt;reasons&lt;/em&gt;. You'll be half way a transaction and you'll have to deal with it somehow, either queuing that
last write and hoping &lt;em&gt;Service 6&lt;/em&gt; comes back soon or rolling back the whole transaction which would mean deleting from
the other services and returning an error, there are ways to solve this, but usually it doesn't need to be this hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;When should I go synchronous?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, it will depend on the use case you're implementing and how critical it is to
return the exact data at the moment the request was done, usually there's some tolerance to
return slightly stale data, but things like &lt;em&gt;credit accounting&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;warehouse availability&lt;/em&gt; or
anything that was to do with resources being consumed in real time are good candidates for
sync calls and all the complexity they involve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Choreography vs Orchestration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's a good analogy in the &lt;em&gt;microservices&lt;/em&gt; world and how they handle &lt;em&gt;things&lt;/em&gt; happening
within the system, let's call those things &lt;em&gt;events&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's say there are two types of &lt;em&gt;events&lt;/em&gt;, those which make the system &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; something, for example,
in an e-commerce website it could be a user bought something, and those which make the system &lt;em&gt;change&lt;/em&gt;
its status, for example, update some records in the database o send a request to another service. The
first ones, let's call them &lt;em&gt;external events&lt;/em&gt; because they're triggered by an external actor, maybe the
user or an external system consuming our API, these &lt;em&gt;external events&lt;/em&gt; are the ones triggering the second
ones, let's call them &lt;em&gt;internal events&lt;/em&gt; because it's the system updating itself. So, &lt;em&gt;external events&lt;/em&gt; trigger
&lt;em&gt;internal events&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, there are two ways of handling &lt;em&gt;events&lt;/em&gt;, we can either do it via &lt;em&gt;orchestration&lt;/em&gt;, where we have
a service which acts as the &lt;em&gt;master&lt;/em&gt; of the transaction, telling all the other services involved in it
what to do, what to update. Just like a Conductor does in an Orchestra, it tells all the other musicians
(services) when to play they part, how to play it and so on. The other way is more like a &lt;em&gt;choreography&lt;/em&gt;,
where given an &lt;em&gt;event&lt;/em&gt; every service knows how to handle it and how to react to it, just like dancers who
know how and where to move or what do do when a certain part of the song is played.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good architectures are a mix of both approaches and good architects know when to use either of those
depending on the business needs and the use case they're modeling. Unfortunately there's no recipe
to decide, gaining experience designing systems and making mistakes are the only way to learn, although
reading about others experience, having clear concepts on how distributed systems and networks work and
a good understanding of the problem at hand we're solving are a good starting point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Rely on data, not services&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We spoke about &lt;em&gt;low coupling and high cohesion&lt;/em&gt; in &lt;em&gt;microservices&lt;/em&gt; in a previous article, relying on
a service to be up in order for some other service to be able to do what it's supposed to do is some
form of &lt;em&gt;coupling&lt;/em&gt;, you are letting an independent system fail because another is feeling unwell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For services to be independent, every service should have a copy of the data they need to answer at least
basic queries, this doesn't mean you'll directly update the copies, you need to define which service is going
to be your &lt;em&gt;source of truth&lt;/em&gt; for a specific piece of data and perform all the write operations for it to &lt;strong&gt;that&lt;/strong&gt;
service and then, somehow, update the copies. You can rely on &lt;em&gt;internal events&lt;/em&gt; to do this, every time an
&lt;em&gt;external event&lt;/em&gt; triggers an update on the &lt;em&gt;source of truth&lt;/em&gt; for a give piece of data, you can fire up
an &lt;em&gt;internal event&lt;/em&gt; to make the services keeping a copy update their local copies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By doing this you can still serve a read-only version of the data for some use cases even if the source of
truth is down, if it's, for example, an e-commerce and the source of truth for the catalog is, for example,
the &lt;em&gt;Inventory Service&lt;/em&gt;, you can still serve the catalog even though the users won't be able to purchase
anything, they still can save them to their &lt;em&gt;wishlist&lt;/em&gt; and browse the website, this lets you gracefully
degrade your system if there are problems with some services, you just show an error message or hide the options
or have alternate workflows until the systems supporting the degraded use case are back up and running.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if a service is down and misses some updates from the source of truth?, well, depending on how you propagate
the updates, you can do several things. You can use a queuing system like &lt;em&gt;ZeroMQ&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;RabbitMQ&lt;/em&gt; to propagate
the updates, so, if a service is down, the updates will be waiting on the queue to be consumed once the service
is up, if you're using HTTP calls, you can have your worker retry the failed requests after a &lt;em&gt;back-off&lt;/em&gt; time or
write the payload to a given location so, when the other service comes up, an &lt;em&gt;init&lt;/em&gt; script checks that location,
reads whatever is there and marks those messages as &lt;em&gt;consumed&lt;/em&gt;, there are multiple ways to deal with this problem,
most of them will depend on the technology you're using.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Eventual consistency&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you deal with distributed systems and distributed information, chances are, some copies will be stalled
for a period of time, this means, information will always be flowing through the &lt;em&gt;pipes&lt;/em&gt; of your system, the only
way you will have total consistency is if you stop writing and wait some time. Even in monolithic systems, what you
show to the user is stale most of the time, let's say, for example, a website listing used articles for sale, when
the search page is served to the user, depending on the traffic, there will be probably 10ths or hundreds of new
articles the user won't see unless they refresh the page or we have a pushing mechanism in place. So, how important is
it really to show the most updated information available to the user?, truth is, is not that critical in most cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For building reports though, you should always query from your sources of truth, this could be tricky on a distributed
system where your source of truth varies depending on the information you're looking for and it's not a single database
where you can run a SQL query and join everything together. You could rely also on &lt;em&gt;internal events&lt;/em&gt; to build a reporting
database while the relevant events are happening instead of querying everything when a report is requested, this way you'll
always have relevant business data to produce reports on top of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's no silver bullet to solve the problems that come with distributed computing, however, there are strategies
to help you discover the best way to deal with certain problems for your specific use case, try to use choreography
where possible and orchestrate the flows that need to be completely synchronous, always try to find the easiest solution,
keep in mind that sometimes the easiest way to solve a problem is the hardest to implement, but benefits will be seen
in the future, when you need to debug a failure or scale, or even extend your system with more features or plugging more
microservices in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, always prefer choreography and async communication when possible instead of orchestration and sync calls between
services, this doesn't mean you should avoid it at all cost as there are use cases that need that approach. A good architect
knows that the best way to solve a problem is not following strictly one and only one approach, it's combining different
concepts and ways around it and adapting them to the specific problem to achieve an efficient and elegant solution. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Recommended readings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2KgY6qh"&gt;Building Microservices&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href="https://samnewman.io/"&gt;Sam Newman&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.martinfowler.com/bliki/CircuitBreaker.html"&gt;Circuit Breaker&lt;/a&gt; by Martin Fowler &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://specify.io/concepts/microservices"&gt;Introduction to Microservices&lt;/a&gt; by Oliver Wolf &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://blog.christianposta.com/microservices/why-microservices-should-be-event-driven-autonomy-vs-authority/"&gt;Why Microservices Should be Event Driven&lt;/a&gt; by Christian Posta &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://blog.bernd-ruecker.com/event-command-transformation-in-microservice-architectures-and-ddd-dd07d5eb9656"&gt;Event command transformation in microservice architectures and DDD&lt;/a&gt; by Bernd Rücker  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://iffm.me/my-take-on-microservices.html"&gt;My take on Microservices&lt;/a&gt; by me :-)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Blog"></category><category term="software engineering"></category><category term="microservices"></category></entry><entry><title>My take on microservices</title><link href="//iffm.me/my-take-on-microservices.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-11-30T00:00:00+04:00</published><updated>2017-11-30T00:00:00+04:00</updated><author><name>Israel Fermín Montilla</name></author><id>tag:iffm.me,2017-11-30:/my-take-on-microservices.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;There's been a lot of stuff going on these days on &lt;em&gt;Software Engineering&lt;/em&gt;, it's hard to catch up on everything 
I would like to. I try to go one topic at a time and now, also because we are working with this at the office,
I'm hooked into microservices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Microservices …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;There's been a lot of stuff going on these days on &lt;em&gt;Software Engineering&lt;/em&gt;, it's hard to catch up on everything 
I would like to. I try to go one topic at a time and now, also because we are working with this at the office,
I'm hooked into microservices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Microservices is a new word for an old concept, a concept I thought I will never see or play with in real life 
back in my University years, I remember my &lt;em&gt;Software Engineering&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Distributed Systems&lt;/em&gt; professors talking
about web services and &lt;em&gt;API&lt;/em&gt;s and huge systems at IBM,
Sun Microsystems and Oracle, SOAP and REST interfaces and how they interacted with each other and, also, the mighty
Enterprise Service Bus with producers and consumers in Java, BPEL and C#, a very abstract
concept for me to grasp at that time and I thought &lt;strong&gt;the only place&lt;/strong&gt; you could see that was working at &lt;strong&gt;huge&lt;/strong&gt;, corporate
companies like the ones I mentioned above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nowadays, &lt;strong&gt;any&lt;/strong&gt; internet &lt;em&gt;startup&lt;/em&gt; can grow at a &lt;strong&gt;huge scale&lt;/strong&gt; and you can play around with this kind of technologies 
if you're lucky enough to be part of one of those projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was lucky to be part of the &lt;em&gt;dubizzle&lt;/em&gt; team, a classifieds website that operates at a &lt;strong&gt;massive scale&lt;/strong&gt; here in the middle east,
the architecture is a huge legacy &lt;strong&gt;monolithic application&lt;/strong&gt; with all of the core functionality and several services surrounding this legacy app.
These services are, in my opinion, mostly &lt;strong&gt;poorly integrated&lt;/strong&gt; and fault tolerance &lt;strong&gt;is not the rule&lt;/strong&gt;, sometimes error responses
are silenced and bypassed which is quite bad. Also, the integration goes over &lt;em&gt;HTTP&lt;/em&gt;, which could be very unreliable
even within the internal network and gives you a lot of headaches when you need to
integrate more and more services. But the whole point of migrating to &lt;em&gt;microservices&lt;/em&gt; is to solve all those issues and have a better
engineered platform to keep both product and tech as happy as possible and be able to move faster at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We dedicated some time now to study &lt;strong&gt;best practices&lt;/strong&gt; for implementing a microservices based architecture and built some proof of concepts and
deployed one of them to production here are some of my key learning and good practices taken from what I've read and personal experience actually
building stuff at &lt;em&gt;dubizzle&lt;/em&gt; and playing around with technology on my personal projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;APIs should be business bounded&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a common mistake to build &lt;em&gt;API&lt;/em&gt;s as simple &lt;em&gt;CRUD&lt;/em&gt; interfaces for &lt;em&gt;domain entities&lt;/em&gt;.
This means, all the &lt;em&gt;business logic&lt;/em&gt; must be written and rewritten in the &lt;em&gt;clients&lt;/em&gt;, so, if you have, for instance, a &lt;em&gt;web client&lt;/em&gt;,
a &lt;em&gt;desktop application&lt;/em&gt;, an &lt;em&gt;Android&lt;/em&gt; and an &lt;em&gt;iPhone&lt;/em&gt; mobile apps, well, you can count yourself
how many times you'll have to write the &lt;em&gt;business logic&lt;/em&gt; surrounding those &lt;em&gt;data models&lt;/em&gt; with a &lt;em&gt;CRUD API&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have to build your API to encapsulate business processes, not just the objects creation and manipulation, so a single &lt;em&gt;API&lt;/em&gt; call,
triggers all the needed processes to fulfill the request or the query the client just gave to the server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Services must be independent units&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means, &lt;strong&gt;you must think&lt;/strong&gt; of each &lt;em&gt;microservice&lt;/em&gt; as a project or a &lt;em&gt;product&lt;/em&gt; on its own, this means each &lt;em&gt;service&lt;/em&gt; 
has its own &lt;em&gt;box&lt;/em&gt; and its own &lt;em&gt;release pipeline&lt;/em&gt; and its own &lt;em&gt;life cycle&lt;/em&gt;, but also, they don't rely on each other to function.
This means, if your &lt;em&gt;invoicing service&lt;/em&gt; is down, your &lt;em&gt;payment service&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;don't need to suffer&lt;/strong&gt; because of this, you can always accept payments from your users and send the invoices later,
when your &lt;em&gt;invoicing service&lt;/em&gt; comes up again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Rely on data, not services&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the previous example you might be thinking "dude, but if the &lt;em&gt;invoicing service&lt;/em&gt; is down when the &lt;em&gt;payment service&lt;/em&gt; hits it, how will it know
it needs to send an invoice to a user?". Well, you need some way to let it know once it wakes up, some &lt;em&gt;data sharing&lt;/em&gt; mechanism like a shared
database (which is in general a bad idea because it creates &lt;em&gt;coupling&lt;/em&gt; between our services) or some sort of &lt;em&gt;caching&lt;/em&gt; on the services that needs
to &lt;em&gt;consume&lt;/em&gt; that data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our example, we could make the &lt;em&gt;payment service&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;invoicing service&lt;/em&gt; share the same database, or, have a good separation of
concerns and lower the &lt;em&gt;coupling&lt;/em&gt; and, since &lt;em&gt;invoicing&lt;/em&gt; needs to know about &lt;em&gt;payments&lt;/em&gt; but, &lt;em&gt;payments&lt;/em&gt; have no need to know about &lt;em&gt;invoicing&lt;/em&gt;,
we can just have a &lt;em&gt;caching&lt;/em&gt; mechanism in place in our &lt;em&gt;invoicing service&lt;/em&gt; and have a copy of the needed data about &lt;em&gt;payments&lt;/em&gt; in order
to generate &lt;em&gt;invoices&lt;/em&gt;, of course, this will add some complexity to our system because we need to be fault tolerant and make sure the data
still reaches the &lt;em&gt;cache&lt;/em&gt; if the &lt;em&gt;invoicing service&lt;/em&gt; is down and we need to put some cache update processes in order to keep it up to date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;High cohesion, low coupling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a principle borrowed from &lt;em&gt;Object Oriented Programming&lt;/em&gt;, let's remember what they mean&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Coupling&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;coupling&lt;/strong&gt; is the degree of interdependence between software modules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means, if two &lt;em&gt;modules&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;functions&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;services&lt;/em&gt; rely too much on each other, chances are if I make a change on one, I'll have to make
a change on the other one to compensate, this makes our code and architecture less orthogonal, which means exactly that, a change in one
part of the system, will affect other unrelated parts, just like driving a helicopter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Cohesion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;cohesion&lt;/strong&gt; refers to the degree to which the elements inside a module belong together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means, it's a measure of how much the &lt;em&gt;elements&lt;/em&gt; inside a &lt;em&gt;module&lt;/em&gt; belong together, not necessarily they rely on each other, but they
all &lt;strong&gt;work together&lt;/strong&gt; towards a common objective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general &lt;em&gt;cohesion&lt;/em&gt; is increased if:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All the &lt;em&gt;elements&lt;/em&gt; in the &lt;em&gt;module&lt;/em&gt; have much in common. This means, access the same set of data, for example.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;em&gt;elements&lt;/em&gt; in the &lt;em&gt;module&lt;/em&gt; carry out a &lt;strong&gt;small&lt;/strong&gt; number of &lt;strong&gt;related&lt;/strong&gt; activities. This means, each member of the
module does one and only one thing related to the task without side effects  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By keeping &lt;strong&gt;related functionality&lt;/strong&gt; together, we are automatically increasing &lt;em&gt;cohesion&lt;/em&gt; and lowering &lt;em&gt;coupling&lt;/em&gt;, and this is exactly
what we want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What does this mean in microservices?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, it's easy to think of &lt;em&gt;coupling&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;cohesion&lt;/em&gt; withing the same computer program or the same code base, but in &lt;em&gt;microservices&lt;/em&gt; this
means exactly the same, &lt;strong&gt;keep related functionality together&lt;/strong&gt; so you don't have that logic spread all over the place and duplicated
in more than one service. This also mean, keep services using similar or related data together, either logically or physically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;One hit, one transaction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means, avoid distributed transaction at all costs, they are difficult to implement and even more difficult to debug if something
goes wrong, ideally one &lt;em&gt;write&lt;/em&gt; operation to your system should directly affect &lt;strong&gt;one&lt;/strong&gt; service, what happens &lt;em&gt;offline&lt;/em&gt; could be a different
story. For example, we could have our &lt;em&gt;payments service&lt;/em&gt; which deals with a third party payment gateway to charge our users' credit cards,
to keep things under &lt;em&gt;Single Responsibility Pattern&lt;/em&gt; (SRP), we will have a separate &lt;em&gt;invoicing service&lt;/em&gt; which handles generating and
sending invoices to the users (I know, we could separate things even more by having a separate &lt;em&gt;notification service&lt;/em&gt; that handles
sending the emails but let's keep it at this level for the sake of simplicity). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, the only thing my client needs to know is &lt;em&gt;I need to make a payment&lt;/em&gt;, whatever happens afterwards it's not my client's problem, it
only needs to hit the &lt;em&gt;payments service&lt;/em&gt; with the needed &lt;em&gt;payload&lt;/em&gt; and get the response to show it to the user. What happens under the hood
is my &lt;em&gt;payments service&lt;/em&gt;'s problem, it needs to &lt;em&gt;somehow&lt;/em&gt; notify the &lt;em&gt;invoicing service&lt;/em&gt; that it needs to email an invoice to a specific
user, this has to happen &lt;em&gt;offline&lt;/em&gt;, either we start a separate &lt;em&gt;thread&lt;/em&gt; or use a message queue for it and we notify either generating an
&lt;em&gt;event&lt;/em&gt; or via an &lt;em&gt;HTTP&lt;/em&gt; call, but this needs to happen offline and be fault tolerant so we don't keep the &lt;em&gt;client&lt;/em&gt; waiting for something
that is &lt;em&gt;our&lt;/em&gt; internal process, as well as updating the inventory, generating accounting ledger entries, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Choreography over orchestration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is, to me, one of the most important best practices I've learned then it comes to microservices oriented architecture, when we think of
distributed transactions we often have some sort of &lt;em&gt;director&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;conductor&lt;/em&gt;, which is the service that initiated the transaction, it will
know, what needs to happen and in which order, also, it will be the responsible to roll everything back if any part of the transaction fails,
transactions need to be &lt;em&gt;Atomic&lt;/em&gt;, right?. This is a very dangerous approach because, if something goes wrong while performing the transaction,
nothing can guarantee something won't happen while rolling it back, leaving the system in an inconsistent state and giving us lots of
headaches down the road when having to debug some weird behavior in our system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best way to implement these kind of &lt;em&gt;distributed&lt;/em&gt; transactions, i.e., business processes that need to update more than one service
is through &lt;em&gt;Choreography&lt;/em&gt;, if you think about a &lt;em&gt;choreography&lt;/em&gt;, there's no &lt;em&gt;conductor&lt;/em&gt;, everyone knows what they need to do, where they
need to go, the only signal is the music. This means, in &lt;em&gt;microservices&lt;/em&gt;, we just need to &lt;em&gt;notify&lt;/em&gt; everyone &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; happened, and
the concerning &lt;em&gt;services&lt;/em&gt; will react accordingly, either updating their database, emitting another &lt;em&gt;event&lt;/em&gt; or sending a notification to
the user.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to properly implement &lt;em&gt;choreography&lt;/em&gt; we need to build &lt;em&gt;resilient&lt;/em&gt; services by putting in place fault tolerance logic or processes
so, if some service fails to react, it can heal itself or someone gets notified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Don't rely on HTTP&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/L._Peter_Deutsch"&gt;Peter Deutsch&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Gosling"&gt;James Gosling&lt;/a&gt; wrote about the
&lt;em&gt;8 fallacies of distributed computing&lt;/em&gt; and the first one was&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The network is reliable&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A million things can happen when you rely on the network, maybe the requests times out, maybe there's a broken link, maybe subnet permissions
were changed maybe the host we are trying to reach is unavailable, maybe a rat ate a network cable, lots of things can happen and we are
not in control of all of them, even withing our own private network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I'd recommend instead is to have a &lt;em&gt;communication layer&lt;/em&gt; in the form of a &lt;em&gt;message bus&lt;/em&gt;, it can be a &lt;em&gt;queue&lt;/em&gt; like 
&lt;a href="https://www.rabbitmq.com/"&gt;RabbitMQ&lt;/a&gt; or a &lt;em&gt;data streaming pipeline&lt;/em&gt; like &lt;a href="https://kafka.apache.org/"&gt;Apache Kafka&lt;/a&gt;
of course there will be a bit of network communication between your services and the communication
layer, or your services and the database system, but that's being taken care of by the corresponding drivers or libraries or deal with those,
so, you can assume they're fault tolerant and the data will reach its destination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There will be cases where you can't avoid rely on &lt;em&gt;HTTP&lt;/em&gt; or any network protocol, for example, you need to serve your website somehow, and
you need to query your services somehow too, so, in this case I'd recommend to go for a &lt;em&gt;REST API&lt;/em&gt; or whatever protocol you prefer for external
communication (third party services and &lt;em&gt;client-server&lt;/em&gt;) and using a &lt;em&gt;message bus&lt;/em&gt; for inter-service communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;A note about the fallacies&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people will say that the &lt;em&gt;8 fallacies of distributed computing&lt;/em&gt; are obsolete nowadays because there are tools already that handle
everything for us, replication, secure networking, authentication, networks are sophisticated so, latency is not a problem anymore but,
just because &lt;em&gt;someone&lt;/em&gt; is taking care of &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; for us, doesn't mean that &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; isn't there, imagine building a system without
these tools, you'll have to face them anyways, besides, there are countries where the computer networks are not as good as in the US or
Europe for example, so, I wouldn't say these &lt;em&gt;fallacies&lt;/em&gt; are becoming irrelevant. Even if you're not implementing replication or security
yourself, you need to think about it and use &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; that handles that for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Recommended readings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://amzn.to/2AkhBdU"&gt;Building Microservices&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href="http://samnewman.io/"&gt;Sam Newman&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://amzn.to/2Am0eZW"&gt;RESTful API Design: Best Practices in API Design with REST&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/mattbiehl"&gt;Matthias Biehl&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://amzn.to/2ngI1dI"&gt;The Pragmatic Programmer&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dave_Thomas_(programmer)"&gt;David Thomas&lt;/a&gt; and 
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andy_Hunt_(author)"&gt;Andrew Hunt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coupling_(computer_programming)"&gt;Coupling (computer programming)&lt;/a&gt; (Wikipedia article)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cohesion_(computer_science)"&gt;Cohesion (computer science)&lt;/a&gt; (Wikipedia article)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fallacies_of_distributed_computing"&gt;Fallacies of distributed computing&lt;/a&gt; (Wikipedia article)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.infoworld.com/article/3114195/system-management/the-8-fallacies-of-distributed-computing-are-becoming-irrelevant.html"&gt;The 8 fallacies of distributed computing are becoming irrelevant&lt;/a&gt; build your own opinion, are they?, comment!.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Blog"></category><category term="software engineering"></category><category term="microservices"></category></entry></feed>