<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>/dev/isra/blog/* - personal</title><link href="//iffm.me/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="//127.0.0.1:8000/feeds/personal.tag.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>//iffm.me/</id><updated>2021-10-05T00:00:00+04:00</updated><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title>7 tips to be a more productive engineer</title><link href="//iffm.me/7-tips-to-be-a-more-productive-engineer.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-10-05T00:00:00+04:00</published><updated>2021-10-05T00:00:00+04:00</updated><author><name>Israel Fermín Montilla</name></author><id>tag:iffm.me,2021-10-05:/7-tips-to-be-a-more-productive-engineer.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As Software Engineers, we are not measured by how much we know about computer
science, data structures and algorithms, at least not after we pass the interview.
At the job the story is completely different, we can be the best programmers in
the company, we can know our way around …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As Software Engineers, we are not measured by how much we know about computer
science, data structures and algorithms, at least not after we pass the interview.
At the job the story is completely different, we can be the best programmers in
the company, we can know our way around the languages we work on and write code
with the eyes closed but, none of that matters if we produce no value. Our value
comes in many forms, code and working, scalable and robust software is one of those
ways, but we can't forget we are part of an engineering team and also keep in mind
that &lt;a href="https://iffm.me/software-engineering.html"&gt;Software Engineering is more than writing code&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of our value comes in the form of working software, performance and resources
optimizations, architecture and software design RFCs and so on, these tasks
require a high level of concentration which means our ability to produce high
value work is constrained by the amount of continuous uninterrupted time we have.
Along with that, we also produce value in meetings, by aligning priorities and
work with other engineering teams and also within our team when we work with other
engineers, by reviewing code and other forms of collaborative work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ideally, we need to maximize the amount of high impact work we do as engineers,
this usually has to do with the tasks that require a higher level of focus, but
we can't neglect the other kinds of work we need to do as well. To 
do this, we need to maximize the amount of uninterrupted time we have during our
working hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are seven practices that have worked for me, hopefully they will work for 
you too. Let's get it on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Have a daily prioritized list&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This looks like a no-brainer, right? and yet, a lot of people seems to fail in
using them. I love lists, I make lists for almost everything: my daily work, 
my personal projects, what I need when I go to the supermarket...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I keep a daily TODO list and I manage priorities with colors:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Red:&lt;/strong&gt; for high impact or urgent work, things that need to be done ASAP or
things that, when done, will have a high impact on the projects I'm maintaining&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Yellow:&lt;/strong&gt; for things that will have impact, but not as much and can wait a bit
to get some attention, for example, looking into an error that pops out from time
to time in the logs or reading about some technology I will need to use some time
in the future. It's good to tackle them before they become red.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blue:&lt;/strong&gt; for things with low to no impact but would be fun or nice to do.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I usually mark in &lt;strong&gt;bold&lt;/strong&gt; the ones that require deep focus to be done, these 
visual conventions help me navigate my list easier than &lt;em&gt;P1&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;P0&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;P2&lt;/em&gt; or
a numeric approach to set priorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't finish my TODO list every day, to be honest, there are always a lot of
things to tackle and it's impossible to get everything done in one day, plus,
every day something new comes up, someone has a new request, someone writes a new
RFC I need to read and comment, so, I keep adding tasks to the list as they come
up and prioritize them later unless they're explicitly urgent. Whatever I can't
finish today gets spilled for &lt;em&gt;tomorrow's&lt;/em&gt; list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also do my lists in advance, I prepare &lt;em&gt;tomorrow's&lt;/em&gt; list &lt;em&gt;today&lt;/em&gt; by end of day,
that way I don't have to do it &lt;em&gt;tomorrow&lt;/em&gt; and I can just review it, and get to
it after I have my coffee in the morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, you'll need to keep your lists somewhere, for this, really, whatever
floats your boat, some people use &lt;a href="https://www.notion.so/"&gt;Notion&lt;/a&gt;, some others
prefer &lt;a href="https://evernote.com/"&gt;Evernote&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://keep.google.com"&gt;Google Keep&lt;/a&gt;
also seems to be a very popular option. At &lt;a href="https://careem.com/careers"&gt;Careem&lt;/a&gt;
we use &lt;a href="https://www.atlassian.com/software/confluence"&gt;Confluence&lt;/a&gt;
internally as a knowledge base solution for all things documentation, the thing
I like about &lt;a href="https://www.atlassian.com/software/confluence"&gt;Confluence&lt;/a&gt; is that
it gives every user a &lt;em&gt;personal&lt;/em&gt; space, I keep my daily TODO in my personal
space as private notes for myself, it's very convenient because I don't have to
have yet another tool, it's work and it's protected by all the security measures
we have at &lt;a href="https://careem.com/careers"&gt;Careem&lt;/a&gt; and I'm usually logged in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This system helps me keep focused and by creating a new page every day, I can
look back and keep track of everything I've worked on and when while also making
sure I focus only on unfinished tasks and remove the noise of finished tasks from
my view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Be intentional with your time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have you ever wondered how it is possible to deliver so much stuff at school or
uni and why we're not able to deliver as much at work?, the answer is, we had a
routine, more or less. We knew every day we were going to have Calculus I
from 10:00 to 12:30, then Algorithms II from 13:00 to 14:30, then 3 hours free,
then back to classes from 18:00 to 19:45, it was predictable, we would use those
3 hours to study, work on a project, have lunch, socialize or a combination of
those, every day was planned and we could schedule in advance what to do. At work
it's a bit more difficult, we have 8 hours of semi-random activities. When I
realized this, I thought it makes sense to give some order to that chaos and
make a routine for myself so that I could use my time in a more predictable manner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One book that changed the way I think and reason about time is &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/31287110-master-your-time-master-your-life"&gt;Master your time
master your life&lt;/a&gt;
by productivity coach &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/author/show/22033.Brian_Tracy"&gt;Brian Tracy&lt;/a&gt;.
In this book, Tracy mentions that there are multiple types of time in life and
one needs to be able to identify what kind of time you have at the moment
to know how you should use it as well as what kind of time a task requires in 
order to know when to do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At &lt;a href="https://careem.com/careers"&gt;Careem&lt;/a&gt; we have what we call &lt;em&gt;focus time&lt;/em&gt;, which
are blocks where no group meetings are allowed, only pairing for problem-solving
or making progress on a task, we also have a no-meetings day, so, I schedule
all my high-focus work at those times. Before we had these policies, I used to
schedule 2 hours every day where I didn't accept any meetings or interruptions,
muted all notifications and just focused on that type of tasks, whether it was
writing code, working on some architecture or designing a solution to implement
it later, I just focused on that during the time I blocked for this high focus
work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I do all my collaborative work on the rest of the time I have, we usually
have some time in-between meetings so I use that to read RFCs, review code and
sometimes socialize.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're taking nothing else from this blog post, take only this point, &lt;strong&gt;Be
Intentional with your time&lt;/strong&gt;, time is too limited and too precious to use it
in a random way, &lt;strong&gt;be intentional&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Be defensive with time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you often find yourself attending more meetings than you feel you should?, or
stuck in a meeting having no idea why you're there?. Learning to say &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; is a
skill you need to master, I had some hard time mastering this skill for many
reasons, our inner nature is to help others, at least mine, I used to say no
very rarely and as a result I was usually swamped with work, meetings and other
commitments. Now, if I find a reason to say &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt;, I say &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt;. It's usually for
a reason. I have a limited amount of time every day and I have to use it wisely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For meetings, if I have a clashing event, I directly reject the invitation. All
my current commitments take precedence with respect to new requests. If the
meeting doesn't have a clear objective or agenda I ask for it to be added, if
it's not added, and I have no way to know what's expected in the meeting, I let
the organizer know I won't attend. If the meetings are spilling, I call that into
attention and leave if I have other things to do. This might seem rude as attending
meetings is part of the job but so it organizing and running them, if a meeting
has no information about what to expect, it means someone is not doing their job
organizing it. If the meeting is spilling, it means someone is not doing their job
running it effectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember, as an IC (Individual Contributor) your time is your most valued resource,
don't give it to everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Learn your tools&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This might seem an obvious one, but It's incredible the number of people I know
who just know the basics of everything they use. I spend most of my time... well...
writing, so, my text editor is where I spend most of my productive time. It doesn't
matter what editor you use, whether it's vim or Emacs, vs-code or an IDE, learn
how to use the advanced features. I use vim for most of the things that has to
do with text: coding, writing docs in markdown, notes, etc. I'm constantly
improving my vim config so that I can write code faster and navigate projects more
efficiently. For larger codebases I'm not very familiar with, I do use an IDE, 
we have an IntelliJ license through Careem, so, that's the IDE I use until I'm
familiar with the project so that I can navigate my way through the code, it's
convenient to learn the key shortcuts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other thing I spend most of my time now is the office chat, we use Slack,
so, it's also worth learning how to use it properly, all the key shortcuts as
well as learning to use the search, it's very powerful and you can find almost
anything you can by using the search box instead of navigating through the chats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By becoming a power user of all the things you use, you can then create systems
to help you become more productive, for example, I often mark slack messages
with reactions I can later search for, or set reminders on Slack about something
a colleague said so that I can take action about it. Investing some time in
becoming a power user at work often pays off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Take breaks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This might seem counterintuitive but taking breaks makes you more productive just
because you give your brain some chance to breath, what does this mean?. Have you
ever been working on a feature, debugging an issue and felt blocked? like, you
don't know what to do, what else to try or that the next step should be?, this is
usually because you're locked inside the problem you're trying to solve, think of
it as a box, it's very difficult to find something when you're inside the box, it's
better to take some distance and look at it from a different perspective that lets
you see what you're searching for. It's very difficult to find a failure anywhere
if you're looking at it too closely, you might be looking at the wrong place,
taking some distance and looking at it from afar makes it easier to spot anomalies
and then just zoom-in there again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's exactly what happens when you take a break, you take some distance from
the problem, allowing your brain to look at it from afar, your unconscious mind
will continue working on the problem while you drink a cup of coffee or read
some other material or (if you work from home and have kids) go change some diapers.
Once you come back to the thing you were working on, it will be more clear or,
at least, you'll have some hints on where to go next.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned &lt;a href="https://iffm.me/working-from-home-with-kids.html"&gt;on a previous post&lt;/a&gt;,
I often use the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pomodoro_Technique"&gt;pomodoro technique&lt;/a&gt; 
on my day to day work, I set a timer and I commit to work on a task for, 
say, 30-40 minutes, I focus on the task at hand and only on that, when the 
time in finished, I take a 5min break and then come back to the task for another
30-40min block, this way I make taking breaks part of my work routine and avoid
dawning myself in a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This also applies to taking vacations, at &lt;a href="https://careem.com/careers"&gt;Careem&lt;/a&gt;
we have unlimited vacations policy, this is great because I can take 1 or 2 days off
whenever I feel I'm burnt out and come back refreshed to work. When you're too
tired or burnt out by work, your motivation decreases and your work doesn't come
out as easy or with the same quality, this is also when you consider switching jobs. 
Taking a couple of days off to rest and disconnect from work when a weekend is 
not enough to recover is a wise time investment, for me, after one of those 
hard-deadline, time-sensitive, critical projects I try to take extend the weekend,
at least 1 day, then I come back fresh and ready for another round. I'm not
saying you should abuse these kind of policies, rather use them for your well-being
and mental sanity, take a break when you feel you need it, your body and your
employer will thank you for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Get the most out of meetings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one might sound odd, if you want to be productive you should actually
avoid meetings, right? as long as I'm sitting on a meeting I'm not doing my
job, hence, I'm not producing value. We can agree on part of the statement for
sure but it's not entirely true, meetings are an essential part of the job, we
work with other fellow humans to tell machines what to do, so meeting with other
people is essential to create alignment and decide on further steps, and make
decisions about the underlying tech we are working on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meetings can't be avoided for sure, we can reduce them as much as we want/need
but some kinds of meetings are just unavoidable and we need to learn to live with
that. Not everything is lost, now that we accepted meetings are part of our life,
we can choose to get the most out of them and make them efficient so that we don't
have to meet too many times to discuss the same topics over and over again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This might take a bit of discipline and agreement with your team, but with a few
general practices in your meetings you can make them more efficient:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start and finish on time, don't wait for late joiners, if you're on-time, you're
late by German standards.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have a clear meeting objective and agenda shared previously, this helps everyone
know what will be discussed and prepare accordingly. If you receive a meeting
invitation without an agenda or at least a description, reject it right away&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep the conversation on-topic, call out side tracks and bring everyone again
to the main topic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take notes and share them, this avoids the back and forth after the meetings and
the traditional questions such as "who was going to do X?", "did we decide A or B?"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Share pre-reads in advance and, if you receive a pre-read for a meeting, make
sure you read it before joining&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meetings are a necessary evil, but with discipline you can tame the monster
and make them more effective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Start and stop on time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, this is the most important advice. We often see Engineers working until late
evening, it's not about the hours, it's about the quality of the time you put
into everything you do, I'd rather work 20min on something but really focused
than 4 hours but all over the place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work will always be there, it never ends, if you start and stop working on time
you're not doing anything wrong, it's just the way it should be. Working remotely
this is especially tricky because you don't have the pressure of commuting, you can
stretch a few minutes to wrap up, but that's it!, when it's time, close your laptop
and go to your family, otherwise working after-hours becomes a habit and you won't
be productive during office hours because you'll be thinking on finishing after-hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time management is vital and a very difficult soft skill to develop, it's all about
routines and rituals to me, it takes a lot of will power and discipline to actually
put these personal processes in place but, in my own experience, it's totally worth
the effort, if I miss doing my TODO list one day, I feel bad and a bit lost and
I'm not fully productive that day because I don't have a clear picture of the
priorities. Writing everything down helps you take it out of your system and
take the tasks one by one without the fear of forgetting something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Recommended readings&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Master your time, Master your life by Brian Tracy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deep Work by Cal Newport&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Blog"></category><category term="career"></category><category term="personal"></category><category term="productivity"></category></entry><entry><title>The pain of moving</title><link href="//iffm.me/the-pain-of-moving.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-04-23T00:00:00+04:00</published><updated>2021-04-23T00:00:00+04:00</updated><author><name>Israel Fermín Montilla</name></author><id>tag:iffm.me,2021-04-23:/the-pain-of-moving.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;There are only few things in life which are as painful, annoying, energy and
time consuming as moving, yes, shifting places is a pain in the... you know.
There are a lot of unknowns and that baffles me: new rent, new neighborhood,
am I going to like it? is it …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;There are only few things in life which are as painful, annoying, energy and
time consuming as moving, yes, shifting places is a pain in the... you know.
There are a lot of unknowns and that baffles me: new rent, new neighborhood,
am I going to like it? is it going to worth the money I'm spending in rent?
Is the new landlord going to be an asshole at some point? then... the new
house, things are never as advertised, they'll show you only what they want you
to see, Real Estate agents are very good at distracting you from details during
the site visit, there's only so much you can see in a few minutes in the property
and that's a huge monster under the bed that will come back and bite you later on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've moved a handful of times because I don't like it, yes, it's very exciting to
be at a new place and meet new people, but all the process around it is never
straightforward. We recently moved to a bigger place, here in Dubai, I believe
the biggest expense is paying the rent, so we delayed it as much as we could, then
COVID gave us the perfect excuse to delay it even more. The truth is, we were all
living in a 1 bedroom apartment for over seven years, since we arrived in Dubai.
We lived in the same building, shifted apartments a couple of times within the
same building, we started just the two of us, my wife and I, then Antonietta
was born and now, 4 years later, Elise has come. It became very difficult to
work from home at some point with everyone in the house and my workspace set up
at the dining table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The house&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of COVID, rents were doing down and kept low for a long while, so, COVID
also gave us the opportunity to move from a 1 bedroom apartment in a very old
building, into a brand new 3 bedrooms villa, with a backyard and everything
for the kids to play and bring friends over, and the rest was almost the same as
the apartment. But not everything is as pretty as
it sounds...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;New place means everything is broken&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, it's weird but it's true, I wish I knew this before, we've had many issues
with water-related things. First the kitchen sink was blocked, apparently there
was a lot of dirt in the pipes so it had to be cleaned, we did that, then, suddenly
water stopped coming out of the faucets, I called maintenance and the guy said
the water tank was empty, so, he opened the main stopcock and water started coming
into the tank, 20min after, my recently fixed brand new backyard was flooded.
I called maintenance again and they took about 2h to come, it turned out the
have the float valve, which closes the water once the tank is full, had to be replaced.
This repair had to be done by my landlord, thankfully it didn't take too long to
fix and the landscaping company fixed the grass again at no cost, KUDOS Green
Lawn Landscaping for the GREAT customer support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then... no water again, after troubleshooting I found out the water tank was
empty again, someone closed the main stopcock. No worries, I opened it and after 20min
it was full again, no floods this time but no water was coming either, I guessed
since the tank was empty the pumps might had got air-blocked, I tried to purge them
myself but it didn't work, so I called maintenance again. They managed to purge
the pumps and get everything working again, but they also said I had to replace
the non-return valve, which prevents the water flowing back into the tank when the
pumps are not working because there's enough pressure. Again... has to be
fixed by my landlord.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Stupid warranty policy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes DAMAC, this is you!. Both times I had to call maintenance, the pointed out
the Villa is out of warranty, which I find quite unfair, and I'm speaking for
my landlord here, COVID delayed the handover because he was back home in India and
was unable to flight back into the UAE for a long while, again, because of the
global COVID-19 pandemic, something no one could foresee, it was officially handed
over to him by the end of December 2020 and now, by April 2021, only 4 months
after, warranty is expired. Let's pause here, the house was supposed to have 1
year warranty coverage, yes, &lt;strong&gt;a house&lt;/strong&gt; has only &lt;strong&gt;one year&lt;/strong&gt; of warranty. My
TV has 2 years, my iPod, 3 years, my car, 5 years. A Louis Vuitton bag or a Gucci
pair of shoes have &lt;strong&gt;a life time&lt;/strong&gt; warranty, they can be repaired, anytime,
anywhere, at any store in any country, as many times as you need, all of these
warranties start running since the moment I get the items, not when I paid, not
when they were built, they only start when I have the product in my hands. A
"luxury villa" has only 1 year, which turned out to be 4 months only. You might
think, yes, those are electronics, very small things, OK, let's go back to construction,
my backyard landscaping has 8 years of warranty and the shades I installed have 3 years,
the entire house only 4 months, how is this supposed to be right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Old issues&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When my landlord came to check the water tank the first time, there was no trace of
any float valve, if it was broken it had to be somewhere inside or around the tank,
but there was none, I am sure the valve was not installed since the beginning, same
with the NRV, they were not there. Those were old issues which went undiscovered
because no one was living in the house until now. I am quite sure there are many 
more undiscovered issues I'll be stepping into...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;but...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because the warranty was less than 4 months... you get the point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The furniture&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because we moved from a one bedroom apartment into a 3 bedrooms villa, we had to
buy some new furniture, we went to IKEA and HomeCenter of course, the experience
has been beyond horrible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;IKEA&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The assemblers didn't follow the instructions and now, there's one cabinet pending
for installation among some other additional enhancements for the same unit.
I visited the store, explained everything that happened and they agreed to arrange
a team to do all the things, I get a call from a supervisor to coordinate the date,
we agreed on a Sunday, before noon. The day comes, no one shows up, next day we went
out and I get a call from the driver "sir, I'll be there within 20min", I tell him
"I was expecting you yesterday, I'm about 1h and 20m away" he answers "it's OK
sir, we will be there". I reach the house, no truck is there, I call and the
guy laughs at me and says "we waited 30min and left, we have other customers to
serve", of course I complained a lot, they made me waste my time, I wasn't planing
to come back home and I did because they said they could wait, I visited the 
store again and I'm waiting to coordinate... again... &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;HomeCenter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The delivery of my daughter's bed was scheduled to happen between 13:00 and 17:00,
after hanging up the phone on me multiple times, they showed up almost at 23:00,
I was tired so I just let them do their job and leave, they scratched all of the stairs
and the bed was also all scratched as if it was used for 5 years before reaching
my daughter's room, I complained at the store and to site manager promises to call
me back within 3 days, it's been over a week and nothing has happened&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Horrible after-sales service&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a recurring issue, it seems like all merchants forget about the customer
right after taking their money and the only way to get things done is to stop being
a nice human being, yell and threat to escalate things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this has happened over the past 2 weeks, so... let's see how I solve everything
hopefully quick... let's see what happens"&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Blog"></category><category term="personal"></category><category term="life"></category></entry><entry><title>Work at a company that puts people first</title><link href="//iffm.me/work-at-a-company-that-puts-people-first.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-04-14T00:00:00+04:00</published><updated>2021-04-14T00:00:00+04:00</updated><author><name>Israel Fermín Montilla</name></author><id>tag:iffm.me,2021-04-14:/work-at-a-company-that-puts-people-first.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The title says it all, easier said than done right? the truth is that it takes
a lot of time for some people (and not so long for some others) to find a place
where they feel welcomed and belonging, it's a quite cool feeling when people
appreciate you and …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The title says it all, easier said than done right? the truth is that it takes
a lot of time for some people (and not so long for some others) to find a place
where they feel welcomed and belonging, it's a quite cool feeling when people
appreciate you and makes an effort in making you feel comfortable at work in
every aspect by always taking into account what's important to you and helping
you with that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, I've been working in the software industry since I was studying, and I
have a lot of stories. Most companies value the business first, and that's
completely valid, if the business is OK, everyone is getting paid and everyone
is happy. But I feel I don't last long in this type of companies, I value
flexibility, every company has its rules and every manager has their values and
also set of rules they use to run their teams, but I believe everything needs to
be evaluated in a case by case basis, not everyone has the same conditions
or priorities in life and this is where this approach fails. Let me share a brief
story of my professional life until now and why I've left some of the companies
I worked for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My first job&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first &lt;em&gt;official&lt;/em&gt; job, and by &lt;em&gt;official&lt;/em&gt; I mean, for a company, with a contract
and not doing something kinda freelance for a friend, was with an online news
hub, they scrapped news websites and presented all the headlines from different
sources in a single place, people could customize which sources they preferred 
for certain topics and filter based on that. My job there was to build bots to
scrape multiple sources, extract the content and store it in our system. I was
still doing my undergraduate courses so it was a part-time thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything was going great! salary always on time for about 3 months, then...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the end of the fourth month, I didn't see the salary being credited to my
account, I didn't pay too much attention, maybe there's a delay with the bank
or they didn't process the payroll on time or whatever, I emailed my manager and
I got an auto-response that he was on vacation, half-way into the month I email
my manager's manager asking what happened...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer was &lt;em&gt;yes, you didn't get paid because you're not working with 
us anymore&lt;/em&gt;, I was a bit shocked because no one told me I was let go, they
conveniently forgot to tell me that little detail, wait a minute, this gets way
better, I highlighted exactly that and the answer was amazing: &lt;em&gt;well, Israel,
if you see the contract it says any party can end the employment agreement. It
doesn't explicitly mention any notice, technically we didn't do anything wrong&lt;/em&gt;.
Long story short, I had to threat them with going to the labor authority and
report the issue in order to get my last salary... almost 3 months after.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Lesson learned&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's very bad people owning and managing companies, I know I was undergraduate
but they even used that fact to imply I should be thankful about them paying me
for my work because, and I quote textually, &lt;em&gt;a lot of students would work for 
free just to get the experience&lt;/em&gt;, well, I wasn't one of those students...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My internship, great! until it wasn't&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first professional work experience was on my internship, I did it with a
small local OpenSource consultancy firm, I learned A LOT!, the work environment
was great and fun, workmates were cool, smart and the kind of people who knows
what they're doing. The only bad thing was salary, as I was an intern, my salary
was low, but I was OK, at least I was doing things I was into and learning quite
a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I finished my internship, they offered me a permanent position which I
accepted, they were aware I was still having academic commitments and they were
OK with that. I had to work on my thesis project so, after some time I asked for
some time off to do that, they offered me a room at the office where I could lock
myself up for up to 3 hours a day to fully focus on my thesis, this was awesome but
the only bad thing was it was respected for a bit over a week, after that I started
getting constantly interrupted to work on other things, we went back and forth
with this for a little over 2 months until I decided to quit so I could focus
on my thesis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Lesson learned&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes your priorities and the organization's priorities are not aligned, and
this is fine, when this happens the best thing to do is to part ways. Maybe if
I was given that time off to complete my thesis as I initially requests I would
still be working there. The company, the projects and the team were awesome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Fast forward to my first job in Dubai&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I won't be talking about how I got a job in Dubai and how I got here, &lt;a href="https://iffm.me/new-grads-survival-guide.html"&gt;I wrote
about it before&lt;/a&gt;, I won't write about how cool it was because &lt;a href="https://iffm.me/working-at-dubizzle.html"&gt;I already did it&lt;/a&gt;
but I'll dig a bit deeper on the real reasons behind me leaving that company.
I wrote an &lt;a href="https://iffm.me/bye-bye-dubizzle-hello-careem.html"&gt;article before about it&lt;/a&gt;, but I wasn't completely honest about why
I actually left because I didn't think it was appropriate at that time. By now,
I know people have changed and switched places, and everything is different so
I won't be at risk of exposing anyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The end of the honeymoon&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In October 18th 2016 my first daughter was born, and it was also the day that
marked the beginning of the end for me at that company. See, here in the UAE, the
paternity leave policy at that time was 1 week off, that company gave 2 weeks
and nothing more. Everyone knew my wife and I are here alone, the nearest
relatives we have are in Spain so we were becoming parents all by ourselves,
which is a lot of work, paternity leave is not vacation it's time to support
your wife who just pushed a human being out of her body and now has to breastfeed,
which is very energy-consuming and demanding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, 2 weeks are not enough, 40 days is the recommended resting time for new moms,
I literally had to beg for my line manager to approve 2 extra weeks off from my
annual leave and coming back, everything was changed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My line manager started making my life impossible, I got a terrible performance
review, which I felt was not fair because an incident from over a year and a half
ago was brought up as the reason even though I fixed it in less than 1hr since the
bug affecting subscriptions experience was reported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, my in-laws visited in November, they were staying with us in Dubai for
three months, until January, so, I applied for 2 weeks off in December so that
we could spend some time around Christmas and New Year together and show them
around. In December, the guy announces the following: &lt;em&gt;guys!, there's a lot to
do, so I won't be approving any vacations this month&lt;/em&gt;, my time off request was
rejected and then I got to know another colleague got it approved to go back home
for a relative's wedding and another colleague was also traveling the same month.
I didn't get to spend too much time around either because there was always something
to do, one day, at around 17:30, the guy in question starts packing to leave and
says &lt;em&gt;Israel!, please make sure you close all the zendesk tickets before leaving&lt;/em&gt;.
After he left, I checked our support dashboard... over 30 tickets pending for 
resolution. I was effectively being given all the crappy tasks no one else wanted
to work on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Then I was moved to a different team&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yup, I thought things were going to improve, and they did for a bit, in 2017 I
spoke in 2 conferences and several meetups, mostly about things I was working on
and trying to attract more talent for the company as well. Before one of the 
conferences I got a task on a very short notice before traveling, so, I made it
clear I might not be able to finish it before flying, but I would complete
what I could and leave pointers on how to finish it so someone else could pick
it up and I did exactly that, the night before flying I wrote a very comprehensive
email explaining the approach I was following and detailing which classes needed
to be changed, which methods and why, even left some test cases written to validate
the functionality worked correctly. Coming back from the conference, my new manager
calls me for a meeting, I thought it was something related to the talk I gave
in the conference, but nope... not even close...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He hands me a warning letter, on which grounds?, because &lt;em&gt;I failed to finish
a task and left for a week&lt;/em&gt;, and he also mentioned &lt;em&gt;your team mates say you're
unreliable and they avoid working with you&lt;/em&gt;, I was shocked, no one ever told me
anything like that. A few days after that meeting I asked my colleagues for
feedback and everything I got was positive, so, I figured, either my line manager
was lying to me or my colleagues were not professional enough to speak to me
directly about work-related things they were not happy about with me. In both
cases, I think that's unacceptable in a professional environment, I thought I left
all that "talking behind your back" thing back in high school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyways, the performance review time comes and I'm called for the performance
evaluation meeting, to my surprise, there's my line manager and my old manager
sitting behind the table which I found strange, what was even more strange was
that the person delivering the performance evaluation was my old manager and,
guess what, it wasn't a good one and quite old things from over 2.5 years ago
were brought up, I have to admit I lost my cool in the middle stopped the
evaluation, told my manager &lt;em&gt;You'll have my resignation email in a few minutes&lt;/em&gt;
and left the room, that's when I wrote an email to HR CCing my line manager to
start my notice period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Lesson learned&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The minute you feel something is not right, speak up, complain, talk to people,
highlight it... if you feel it isn't right, then it isn't right, you don't have
take crap from anyone and if someone is giving you a hard time for no apparent
reason, the best thing to do is to part ways, to be honest, looking back I feel I
took too long to leave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;And I joined Careem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I already wrote about joining Careem and why I joined, so, I won't repeat myself
here, but I will point out that I had my second daughter recently (2020) and I was
super scared about it, this didn't go too well with my previous employer and
I have to confess I started interviewing with several companies at the time, had
2 very good offer letters in my hands and was on the final stages for another 2
openings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Things were different this time&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, the only thing which was the same was the paternity leave time, only 2 
weeks, I spoke to my manager about getting an extended paternity leave because 
of COVID, no family was going to be able to come over, airports were closed
(it was by the end of 2020) and forget about traveling to Spain and working from
there for a while... you know... because COVID... and also because my wife's 
passport was expiring. Nothing like this was ever proposed at Careem and he was
quite new in this &lt;em&gt;being a manager&lt;/em&gt; thing so, he did what any new manager would do,
he asked me to go to HR and he would be OK with whatever they decide and, if they
said &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt;, we would find a way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So... I went to HR and explained everything, they were super supportive, they said
&lt;em&gt;hey, there's no such thing as an extended paternity leave, but you can request
time off your annual leave as we have unlimited vacations policy and we will leave
a note highlighting this was for paternity extension&lt;/em&gt;. I did just that, not only
HR and my manager were super supportive, but also my whole team. I got a bit over
a full month to spend at home supporting my wife and taking care of our 4yo
who was staying at home because of the pandemic so that my wife could breastfeed
peacefully, also doing a lot of diaper changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, coming back to work was super flexible, they gave me quite flexible timing
to continue supporting at home while we got back into the routine. I even got a 
great performance review, I am beyond happy about all of this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What about the interviews&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, I understood that very few companies are like this, so... I ended up rejecting
the offers and canceling the last interview rounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My take about everything&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A job is a job, and there's nothing you can do about it, you have it today,
tomorrow no one knows. But not all companies are the same, there are some which
puts the business first. For example, the first company I worked for... maybe they
needed someone cheap to complete the mechanical work of implementing web scrapers
to extract the content from those websites and they just stopped caring after it
was done, I don't know. The one where I did my internship, well, they had projects
to finish for the clients, so, they needed me to work on that, so my thesis and
my graduation goal wasn't a priority for them. My first job in Dubai, well, I
don't know what happened there, but if they had a "people first" kind of philosophy
nothing of that would had happened. Of course, I understand, if the business comes
first, it runs, it generates value and revenue and people gets paid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, on the other hand, we have companies like Careem, maybe supporting my wife
is not their business or priority, but it was something I needed to do so, they
supported me on that. Then, coming back to work and get back into the routine
might be their priority, and also mine, but also family comes first, so... if 
something was happening at home, I had to solve that first and then comes the work.
They could have rushed me into work, but they didn't, we went step by step and
I took only non-critical tasks for a while until everything was settled both at
home and work. They understand that if you put your people first, they will 
care for the business as if it was their own, and that's exactly what I do. I want
to work on a place like this for a very long time, and it's my job to contribute
to its success so I can continue here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you Careem for being Careem.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Blog"></category><category term="career"></category><category term="personal"></category></entry><entry><title>Which languages should I learn?</title><link href="//iffm.me/which-languages-should-i-learn.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-06-01T00:00:00+04:00</published><updated>2020-06-01T00:00:00+04:00</updated><author><name>Israel Fermín Montilla</name></author><id>tag:iffm.me,2020-06-01:/which-languages-should-i-learn.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;There are millions of articles and blog posts out there trying to
tell you what to learn next or which language or technologies are 
worth your attention, things like &lt;em&gt;Top 10 programming languages&lt;/em&gt; or
&lt;em&gt;Learn one of these languages and you'll be done&lt;/em&gt; with some statistics
about language popularity but …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;There are millions of articles and blog posts out there trying to
tell you what to learn next or which language or technologies are 
worth your attention, things like &lt;em&gt;Top 10 programming languages&lt;/em&gt; or
&lt;em&gt;Learn one of these languages and you'll be done&lt;/em&gt; with some statistics
about language popularity but the truth is, none of those make sense
no one can tell you what to learn and you don't need to study whatever
is popular out there all the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Truth is, while popular languages are widely used, also, supply is high,
hence, salaries will tend to be lower, on the other hand, if you learn
the not-so-popular ones, salaries would be higher but you'll end up
most likely having a hard time finding a job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Trends come and go&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatever is popular today, might be considered terrible in the future as well
as what's not so popular today, might be widely used in future, you just have
to see the growth trends in whatever languages or technologies you're into.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Few years back, for example, JavaScript was used only for frontend development
and JQuery was the best thing out there for it, now almost no one uses JQuery
directly, everyone is using react, angular or vue and now you can even find
JavaScript on the backend (not that that's a good thing IMO...).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point is, we should not chase the top 10 most popular technologies, we should
try to find a balance, otherwise we won't really fully learn nor master anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;My view&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that, the first thing we need to do is, work on what's paying your bills.
Few years back, for example, Python was the one paying my bills and it happened to
be the first language I worked with after graduating, I became passionate about it,
to the point that I organized meetups and conferences back home in Caracas - Venezuela
and after that, I only looked for jobs in Python, it was gaining popularity and growing
a lot, I know, I was lucky, but it also makes a point, I was focused on becoming
better on a single thing which were the technologies I was working with at that point
in time, the full stack was Python, Postgres and OpenERP (now it goes by Odoo).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think everyone should start by that, just become better and learn more about
the stack you're currently working with. My last 100% Python job was at my
previous company (dubizzle/OLX), when I joined Careem the stack I worked with
changed to Java, Springboot and MySQL mainly, so I started over, learning a new
framework and a not-so-new language to me. Then, I switched teams and the stack
was Python, Jenkins (groovy) and Terraform, again, learning new things. Then, after
almost 2 years, I again switched teams and the stack was Typescript, Express, Node,
and both MySQL and Postgres and after few months I was changed to a different team again,
the stack also changed and now, this team works on PHP and Go for the most part and
MySQL. Whenever your stack at work changes, focus on learning and mastering that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you master whatever is helping you pay your bills, you can use your spare
time to learn whatever you want, in my opinion you need to know at least one
of those popular languages just to make sure if something unexpected happens 
to your current job, you can find a new one quick. In my case, maybe I've been
just lucky, I know Python, Java and JavaScript and those are three of the most
popular languages out there today. But I also know their popularity won't last forever
and that some less popular languages might pay better salaries because supply is
less and the skills are more rare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone is free to learn whatever they want, but this is how I think about it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Start by what pays your bills:&lt;/strong&gt; this is important, you need to be efficient at
your work and the only way to achieve it is by learning how to use your tools
effectively. This will help you do more in less time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One popular language:&lt;/strong&gt; well, at least one, if you like more than one, go for it,
why learning the popular ones?, this will open the door for more job opportunities,
you never know what will happen and it's better to be prepared to hunt (or be hunted)
for a new role on a different company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One high level language:&lt;/strong&gt; the higher level, the best, I'd go for a language with
a dynamic but strong type system, why? to build things quick. Usually high level
dynamic languages have a huge ecosystem of libraries and frameworks you can leverage
your work on and achieve more writing less code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One lower level language:&lt;/strong&gt; you never know when you'll need either more speed or
write something at system level or even have more control over how the program will
manage memory. Truth is, not all use cases are covered by a High Level object oriented
language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's not too hard to achieve that, you can mix and match languages in all those buckets, 
for example, in most of the cases what pays your bills will be a popular high level
language, that covers the first three, then you'll only need to learn a lower level
programming language to be all setup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you cover that, you can explore other paradigms and incorporate more patterns
and practices from those paradigms and other languages into your every day programming
style, by learning, understanding and practicing is the only way we become better
software engineers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my case, as I know JavaScript/Typescript, Python and Java because of previous jobs,
maybe not all of them at an expert level but at least a general understanding so that
I can tackle most of the day-to-day tasks using them.
I'm focusing on learning Rust, it's a language which is growing and implements interesting
concepts and I've toyed around with Smalltalk and Haskell to see what's there to learn and 
incorporate new practices into my coding. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What's currently on your learning list? let me know on the comments box.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Blog"></category><category term="software engineering"></category><category term="career"></category><category term="personal"></category></entry><entry><title>Engage!</title><link href="//iffm.me/engage.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-05-20T00:00:00+04:00</published><updated>2020-05-20T00:00:00+04:00</updated><author><name>Israel Fermín Montilla</name></author><id>tag:iffm.me,2020-05-20:/engage.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was playing with my daughter the other day, I had work to do but I take breaks
every now and then to pay attention and play or watch some episode of her favorite
cartoons on Netflix as I mentioned &lt;a href="http://iffm.me/working-from-home-with-kids.html"&gt;on a previous article&lt;/a&gt;. 
So, I was waiting for the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was playing with my daughter the other day, I had work to do but I take breaks
every now and then to pay attention and play or watch some episode of her favorite
cartoons on Netflix as I mentioned &lt;a href="http://iffm.me/working-from-home-with-kids.html"&gt;on a previous article&lt;/a&gt;. 
So, I was waiting for the alarm to ring and checking the notifications on my phone
if there was an important email or slack message to reply to or a VictorOps ping
about a production incident, all of that while playing with her &lt;em&gt;Frozen&lt;/em&gt; toys to
rescue &lt;em&gt;Elsa&lt;/em&gt; from &lt;em&gt;Prince Hans&lt;/em&gt; who kept her locked in the castle. When the
break finished, it also meant the play time ended, the alarm rang and I said
something like "oh, it's time for daddy to go back to work" while I started 
getting up she interrupted me "but we didn't play!", then I said "of course we
played, we were rescuing &lt;em&gt;Elsa&lt;/em&gt;" and she threw a killer argument "you were on your
phone". I took a deep breath and realized it was true, truth was, I spent more time
checking on my phone rather than engaging in the game with her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We live in a very distracted world, in a very connected society, we are always
online and not only that, we are always on top of our phones waiting for the
next notification to come so that we know what was the latest event on someone
else's life or the latest comment on something we posted or, in my case, 
what's the latest instant message on my slack workspace. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Always distracted&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seems like we are unable to focus on doing a single thing and getting it done
in one sit, the ability to focus for a large span of time is lost, no matter
what it is, whenever we get a notification or feel the phone vibrating inside 
our pocket, we dump whatever it is we're doing and check what happened, then
we check other apps, then we put the phone away, sometimes we check even if 
it didn't beep!, why? why does a tiny device have such power over ourselves?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Change!&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My daughter's statement made me realize I do that, I have that tendency to always
check my phone, even if I don't have any notification, it made me feel so bad about
myself, I don't want to be dominated by a device, I felt like Pavlov's dog, hardwired
to change my behavior whenever I hear a beep from my phone. So, I decided to change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Take action&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started by eliminating all temptation, I muted all notifications on my personal phone
except for whatsapp and telegram, the only reason to keep those is my family, if they
write I want to reply, but I muted all the groups, I'll check them only when I want to,
same for social media apps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I quit Facebook and Instagram about a year ago and I don't miss them at all, I'm only
on twitter, reddit and linkedin, all of them muted on my phone and I only check them when
I want to, not when they tell me &lt;em&gt;hey, you have a message&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;hey, someone liked something&lt;/em&gt;
same goes for gmail, I check it only when I want to, usually on my laptop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On my corporate phone I have notifications for almost everything, that is basically slack, gmail
and VictorOps, but I have silent hours for slack so I don't get bothered at all times, specially
over the weekend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The most important thing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most important change is not how to setup your notifications on your phone, is deciding
to change yourself and choosing to engage on the activity you're doing &lt;strong&gt;here and now&lt;/strong&gt;, whatever
is in front of you is what's important and should get 100% of the attention, engage!, if I'm playing
with my daughter, I decided to engage 100% and be all into it, if I'm working on a project, I engage
on that and fully focus on it for the time I have or decided to put into it, if I'm talking to someone
I'll be 100% into the conversation, not checking my phone. Some app installed on my
phone is not going to take me away from &lt;strong&gt;here and now&lt;/strong&gt;, because it's the only thing we have and the
only thing we live directly, a message from someone hundreds of kilometers away is not more important
than whatever is in front of you, interacting face to face. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stop letting the algorithm distract you and decide to engage!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Blog"></category><category term="career"></category><category term="personal"></category></entry><entry><title>Bye bye dubizzle, hello Careem!</title><link href="//iffm.me/bye-bye-dubizzle-hello-careem.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-03-30T00:00:00+04:00</published><updated>2018-03-30T00:00:00+04:00</updated><author><name>Israel Fermín Montilla</name></author><id>tag:iffm.me,2018-03-30:/bye-bye-dubizzle-hello-careem.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've been quiet for the last two months, I was a bit busy switching jobs, yes,
after more than three years I decided to leave &lt;em&gt;dubizzle&lt;/em&gt;, part of the &lt;em&gt;OLX&lt;/em&gt;
group and one of the biggest brands here in the United Arab Emirates, for reasons
I won't discuss in this …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've been quiet for the last two months, I was a bit busy switching jobs, yes,
after more than three years I decided to leave &lt;em&gt;dubizzle&lt;/em&gt;, part of the &lt;em&gt;OLX&lt;/em&gt;
group and one of the biggest brands here in the United Arab Emirates, for reasons
I won't discuss in this post and some reasons I'll expose here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My good friend &lt;a href="http://gerardobarcia.com/blog/"&gt;Gerardo Barcia&lt;/a&gt; used to quote a lot
a phrase which author I don't know:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Change is the only constant in our lives&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I liked that, I like to think that one needs to come out of your comfort zone from time
to time as the only way to evolve as a professional and as a human being, when change
comes to you constantly, you're done, when you can seek change easily it's also good,
you learn, you innovate, you become better you put that brain to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was one &lt;em&gt;the thing&lt;/em&gt; I loved about working at &lt;em&gt;dubizzle&lt;/em&gt;, it was dynamic, I got
to work on interesting projects, I got to challenge myself and it was &lt;strong&gt;GREAT!!&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't know what happened or when, but things became just &lt;strong&gt;good&lt;/strong&gt; and then &lt;strong&gt;meh&lt;/strong&gt;, everything
slowed down and I didn't feel challenged anymore, in fact, I felt like I was solving the
same problem over and over and over again, I simply stopped having fun, the projects
I was working on didn't motivate me and I wasn't feeling I was having a positive impact
anymore, so, change didn't come to me, so I started looking for change, trying to be
moved to a different department or a different role and finding a lot of resistance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you stop enjoying something, you should stop doing it and that was exactly what happened,
I stopped enjoying my job at &lt;em&gt;dubizzle&lt;/em&gt;, for several reasons but I believe this one was
the most important one, so I decided to move on. Here in the UAE, there are several big
players in the tech scene: &lt;em&gt;dubizzle&lt;/em&gt; is one of them but not the only one, there's also
&lt;em&gt;Souq&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Namshi&lt;/em&gt; which are e-commerce websites, &lt;em&gt;Fetchr&lt;/em&gt; which is a delivery company and
&lt;em&gt;Careem&lt;/em&gt; which is a ride-hailing company. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I interviewed with several but I wanted to do
something different, I was into classifieds for too long and e-commerce I don't think is
that different, so, when the decision came down to &lt;em&gt;Fetchr&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Careem&lt;/em&gt;, I started digging
deeper into both companies and there was one talk by one of &lt;em&gt;Careem&lt;/em&gt; co-founders, Magnus Olsson,
that made me think, well &lt;em&gt;Fetchr&lt;/em&gt; looks like a great company, also &lt;em&gt;Careem&lt;/em&gt;, but &lt;em&gt;Careem&lt;/em&gt;
has this guy with this amazing story and the will to do something meaningful and you can
see that even in the name of the company, &lt;em&gt;Careem&lt;/em&gt; means &lt;em&gt;generosity&lt;/em&gt; in Arabic language.
So, here I am, being Careem at &lt;em&gt;Careem&lt;/em&gt; and helping &lt;em&gt;improve the people's lives and
build an organization that inspires&lt;/em&gt; one line at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Recommended:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HrSYYmaKmmo"&gt;The video&lt;/a&gt; that made me join &lt;a href="https://careem.com"&gt;Careem&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.glassdoor.com/Overview/Working-at-Dubizzle-EI_IE670451.11,19.htm"&gt;dubizzle in Glassdoor&lt;/a&gt; looks like a lot of people are not happy, I hope they course correct before it's too late&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Blog"></category><category term="career"></category><category term="personal"></category></entry><entry><title>We always evolve</title><link href="//iffm.me/we-always-evolve.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-12-14T00:00:00+04:00</published><updated>2017-12-14T00:00:00+04:00</updated><author><name>Israel Fermín Montilla</name></author><id>tag:iffm.me,2017-12-14:/we-always-evolve.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've been going through code I wrote about two or maybe three years ago while cleaning up my working directory
and archiving old stuff and, I must say: what the hell did I have in my head by that time?, for real, there are
things that are over-engineered, very complicated …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've been going through code I wrote about two or maybe three years ago while cleaning up my working directory
and archiving old stuff and, I must say: what the hell did I have in my head by that time?, for real, there are
things that are over-engineered, very complicated solutions to simple problems, sub-optimal or inefficient code,
a lot of spaghetti code, highly coupled modules (or django apps), all of this to say the least.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know, maybe, in a couple of months (or years) I'll go through the code I wrote today, or yesterday and say the
same thing &lt;em&gt;oh my god! was I stupid or what?&lt;/em&gt;, but I believe this is part of every craftsmanship job like software
engineering, graphic design, cooking and even music. You come out of school with the knowledge, but only experience
doing what you're trained to do will give you elegant practices and make you a good professional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best way to evolve is to &lt;strong&gt;never stop learning&lt;/strong&gt;, read a lot of technical stuff, also master your &lt;strong&gt;soft skills&lt;/strong&gt;,
I wrote it bold because they're as important as your technical ones, try out new ways of doing things, programming
paradigms, new programming languages, new tools to add to your stack and adopt better practices or ease some
pains in your development, testing or deploy process, perhaps your company's or your employer's processes. Only by
learning and gaining knowledge and then putting it in practice you will gain experience and know what works, what doesn't
work and what work betters under some conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowledge is of no value unless you put it into practice.
— Anton Chekhov&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might be asking what made me reflect on this, well, some time ago I wrote about &lt;a href="the-evilness-of-none.html"&gt;&lt;em&gt;The evilness of None&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and
how it is a bad practice to &lt;code&gt;return None&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;return null&lt;/code&gt; from functions when you're expecting the output to meet
certain requirements (internal link). Since I wrote that, I've been going through old projects checking how common
this pattern was on my code and, unsurprisingly, I found some other bad practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, if checking old code and surprising myself with &lt;em&gt;how stupid I was&lt;/em&gt; is something that happens often, it is a good
thing, it means I've learned something I didn't know by the time I wrote that code. So, always move forward but,
from time to time, check backwards not to adopt bad old habits, but to see how much you've learned and also if there's
anything you need to fix on a project you're maintaining.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Blog"></category><category term="software engineering"></category><category term="career"></category><category term="personal"></category></entry><entry><title>PyConPL 2017</title><link href="//iffm.me/pyconpl-2017.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-09-01T00:00:00+04:00</published><updated>2017-09-01T00:00:00+04:00</updated><author><name>Israel Fermín Montilla</name></author><id>tag:iffm.me,2017-09-01:/pyconpl-2017.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Two of my personal goals for this year were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1.- To speak at a local meetup here in Dubai&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2.- To speak at a bigger conference, anywhere&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to my wife, who is always supporting me much more than I support her, I could do
both, first one was at …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Two of my personal goals for this year were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1.- To speak at a local meetup here in Dubai&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2.- To speak at a bigger conference, anywhere&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to my wife, who is always supporting me much more than I support her, I could do
both, first one was at &lt;a href="https://www.meetup.com/Dubytes/"&gt;Dubytes&lt;/a&gt;, also, thanks to my colleague
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/dareenalhiyari?lang=en"&gt;Dareen Alhiyari&lt;/a&gt; who runs that meetup group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second one was at &lt;a href="https://pl.pycon.org/2017/index_en.html"&gt;PyCon Poland&lt;/a&gt;, this year (2017),
my talk &lt;a href="https://speakerdeck.com/iferminm/django-in-the-real-world"&gt;django in the real world&lt;/a&gt; was
accepted and my employer, &lt;a href="https://uae.dubizzle.com/"&gt;dubizzle&lt;/a&gt;, sponsored my trip there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My experience in Poland was great so far, the conference was at &lt;a href="http://www.hotelossa.pl/en/"&gt;huge beautiful venue&lt;/a&gt; 
one hour away from Warsaw, so I arrived one day before so I could walk around Warsaw and see some
historic and touristic places, &lt;a href="https://goo.gl/photos/pyRveSzZ6wAQQwnE6"&gt;the old town is beautiful&lt;/a&gt;,
and that was pretty much all I could see, didn't have time to do any museum before
going to &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arkadia_(shopping_mall)"&gt;Arkadia&lt;/a&gt; do to some shopping,
for my wife and my daughter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Public transportation is quite straightforward, the only issue is you have to ask people to write down
things if you ask for directions, everything is in Polish and it's not pronounced the same way as
written, with some time you get it, but I ended up asking people to write it for me the first day.
People were really helpful, every time I struggled with any of the ticket vending machines, someone
jumped in and helped, even if they didn't speak too much English, they did their best to understand
and help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I finished all my shopping and touristing by 22:30, so I headed to the hotel, which was just in front
of the airport, at the other side of Warsaw, I took the Tram, walked a bit to the main bus station
(I think) and waited for the 175 bus heading to Chopin Airport, at the station I had to use my
Latino defensive skills, some drunk guy tried to steal my wallet, I was carrying a lot of bags, I
was obviously a tourist, but you just don't try to steal something from a South American without at 
least a knife.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I arrived at the Hotel by 23:30, tired, took a bath and went to sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Getting to the conference&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I packed all my stuff, checked out from the hotel after breakfast and headed to the meeting point
at Chopin Airport, conference attendees started to crowd and I started to talk to random people, 
dubizzle asked me to recruit so, I started to try out my skills talking to people, asking what
they do with Python and speaking about what we do and how we do it at dubizzle, some people looked
excited when I talked about employment opportunities, some others not so much, apparently the hot
weather in summer is a deal breaker, the bus arrived, I checked in with the organizers and
boarded, it was a roughly 1hr trip to the venue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Conference&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Experiencing a conference as a speaker and as a normal attendee, is almost the same, as a speaker
people asks you much more questions about what you do and about what you will talk about, I spoke
to a lot of people with the intention of recruiting them, I was impressed about how well prepared
most people were, they had master degrees or pursuing PhD studies, academic titles mean nothing nowadays,
but they do tell you that the person takes care and time on improving himself and gaining more knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was very well organized, and there was always someone from the organizing team available to help
and to answer questions. People were also impressed about the fact that I went all the way from Dubai
to speak at their conference, I was humbled and honored to be there to be honest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the conference I was more into talking to people, I did attend to some talks, but my main
focus was networking and getting people into applying to work at dubizzle or sending me their CV.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My Talk&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'd say it was great, I got a lot of questions, which is a good sign, if you get no questions it means
that people were either not listening or did not understand a single word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm waiting for them to upload the videos from the talks to watch how I really did and some other talks
I was interested in but couldn't attend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really liked the experience, I would definitely encourage everyone to apply to speak at this kind of
conferences, I'll apply to speak at PyConPL next year for sure and will take my family as well, Warsaw
is a beautiful city, full of history and nice people. Will come back for sure!.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, if you're looking for a job and would like to relocate to Dubai, have a look &lt;a href="http://blog.dubizzle.com/uae/job-vacancies/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
at the open positions and leave me a comment, we can talk about it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Blog"></category><category term="personal"></category><category term="speaking"></category><category term="pycon"></category></entry><entry><title>Working at dubizzle</title><link href="//iffm.me/working-at-dubizzle.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-08-16T00:00:00+04:00</published><updated>2017-08-16T00:00:00+04:00</updated><author><name>Israel Fermín Montilla</name></author><id>tag:iffm.me,2017-08-16:/working-at-dubizzle.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;About 4 years ago I got an email through StackOverflow Careers from a woman called
Claudia Verlinden, a very nice Belgian lady who happened to be an HR Manager at a company
in the middle east and she was looking for Software Engineers with experience in Python and
django, so …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;About 4 years ago I got an email through StackOverflow Careers from a woman called
Claudia Verlinden, a very nice Belgian lady who happened to be an HR Manager at a company
in the middle east and she was looking for Software Engineers with experience in Python and
django, so, she asked me if I was interested in applying to one of their open positions
in their Engineering team, I said yes and 2 months later I was boarding a plane and landing
in Dubai, yes Dubai.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My Dubai experience&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a lot of taboo in the west side of the world about the Middle East region, specially
about Arabs, Muslims and Islam in general, they speak a lot about terrorism and how everyone
in the Middle East is a potential terrorist, how Arabs have no sense of humor and they're angry
all the time. Well, I'm here to tell you that none of that is true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, after living almost 4 years in Dubai, a Muslim country, my experience had been nothing
but positive from almost every perspective (still don't like the weather in August), there's
people from everywhere in the world, from countries I didn't know were countries and you get
to see people whose countries had been in war, working together like the best friends in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dubai is one of the safest cities in the world and for me, coming from Caracas, one of the
most violent cities in the world, that's very important. You'll never see a gun if it isn't on
a Policeman's belt, no one will break into your house or car to take that cellphone you left there
or that purse with your documents in the back seat, more important, if you leave something at some
place, even in the street, there's a high chance it will still be there when you're back. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My wife has left her iPhone in restaurants, hospitals and stores more times than I can remember and each and
every time we got it back the same day, they even called me once to tell me "hey, I believe someone you
know left her phone in my store, it's a pink iPhone, anyone you know has a pink iPhone with a Hello Kitty
cover?", yes... that's my wife's.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the heat in summer, which can reach over 50C by August, there are a lot of things to do as a single
or with your family, museums, restaurants, bars, beaches, hiking, desert camping and BBQ, you name it, even
indoors Skying at Sky Dubai in Mall of the Emirates. I'm a declared foodie (I married a chef), and one of
the things I like the most is the huge variety of gastronomy you can find, from Arabic to Russian food, American
burger joints, Asian Cuisine and even Latin restaurants, some Peruvian, Colombian, Argentinean and there's even a Food Truck
serving Arepas and a lot of Venezuelan stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arabs have such an amazing sense of humor, they even joke about bombs and having terrorist cousins,
they get American jokes and they like Jeff Dunham!, they're pretty much like Latinos, they like to
laugh a lot and they're loyal friends, if they can help you in any way, you can be certain they will.
But it needs to work the other way around as well, if they need your help, they will expect you to
help them if it's on your hands, but that's what friendship should be about, right?, relying on each
other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something I realized when I moved here is that not all Arabs are Muslims and not all Muslims are Arabs,
Islam is a wide spread religion in this region, so most Pakistanis, some Indians, also some Filipinos,
Bosnian, and people from the *stan countries are Muslims and they're not Arabs, but also there are a lot
of Catholics and Christians in Lebanon, which is an Arab country, and also in India and Egypt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UAE, and specially Dubai is super liberal to be an Islamic country, you get to see everything, from women
wearing the traditional Abaya and Niqab or Hijab, to women wearing &lt;em&gt;almost&lt;/em&gt; nothing and people is ok with
that. Alcohol is forbidden in Islam, so, it's a bit harder to get, which doesn't mean is hard. Only Muslims
are not allowed to drink, rest of people can get an Alcohol License which will allow you to purchase anything
you want in the authorized stores, if you don't want to get into the (easy) paperwork to get the license, you
can always go have some drinks at a bar or restaurant in a hotel. This was the most shocking change for me as
a Latino, I can't buy beers or rum freely at the supermarket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One last thing I love about Dubai, it's getting more and more like a science fiction movie, seriously,
I don't know why, but these guys ruling the country have a very futuristic vision. Tallest building
in the world (Burj Khalifa), artificial islands (Palm Jumeirah and the one Burj Al-Arab hotel is built on top
of), biggest shopping mall in the world (The Dubai Mall), they are testing flying taxis already and
there's a project to build a Hyperloop train, that will take you
from Dubai to Abu Dhabi in less than 20min, by bus or car it almost 2hr.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Working at dubizzle&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working at a UAE based company, like dubizzle, comes with some perks. But working at one of the most
visited and recognized brands in the country is even better. First of all over 30 different nationalities
converge in the same workplace, different cultural backgrounds. British, Latinos, Indians, Arabs, Pakistanis,
Asians, Europeans, you name it, I sometimes joke with HR everytime I recommend someone from a country we don't have
yet saying "he's a new nationality for out list, we should just hire him to show off" so far we have people from
all of the 5 continents working at dubizzle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To have an idea of how big dubizzle is, we are now part of the OLX group and dubizzle was the only site within
the region that wasn't re-branded to OLX, we got to keep our name and identity because it was a so well established
brand that it would have been more expensive to re-brand it and rebuild it rather that just keep the same brand
as it is, also, we are the only company running a different stack, all of the OLX sites run on PHP, we run in
python and mostly django.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working at a place at this scale is great!, you get to solve very complex and interesting problems, such as optimizing
a service to reduce the response time, might be a caching problem or a database issue, you'll have to look
at the data and make a decision on where to start and you'll have complete freedom to get it done within
reasonable deadlines, of course. This is a very data-driven process, before we do anything we look at numbers,
either from an A/B test or one of our monitoring tools like newrelic and we start analyzing what's happening and
thinking how to approach the problem at hand, we sometimes need to build several proof of concepts and measure
to see what would be the best way to proceed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing I like the most is how everyone is involved on product decisions, like new features, design or workflow
changes, every idea needs to be presented as a spec, with some sort of numbers backing it, either an A/B test or
a market research, results from a poll, anything to back it idea, all the company is involved in these spec reviews:
Engineering, Customer Support, Sales, Finance, Marketing, Management, literally everyone who wants to attend can
do it. The specs are presented and everyone is encouraged to talk, criticize (in a constructive way), make suggestions,
agree, disagree, the idea is to improve the idea and take it from good to awesome or prevent us from building it
if someone finds a good point that proves the spec wrong or too expensive. Everyone has a voice and everyone's voice
is heard. Anyone can have an idea, spec it and take it to spec review, some of the features in our website came from
some engineer who thought it could work and wrote the spec along with the Product Manager and made it live.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, as a new parent, flexibility is very important to me, dubizzle is by far one of the most flexible companies
I've worked at, working hours are from 9:00 to 18:00, but you don't need to be in at 9:00 sharp, strictly, if you
can't make it, either because of traffic or because life happened at home, dubizzle is a very goal-oriented workplace,
so, as long as you're in for your daily team stand-up (which starts by 9:45 - 10:00 in my case) or you message in advance
if you're going to be late, it's ok. But, you need to keep in mind that, sometimes, you'll need to make up some time if
your project is getting late and will miss the deadline. I've had to leave early because my wife or my daughter were not
feeling well, had to take one week off in the middle of a sprint because all of us were sick, in bed, had to come in
late because I had to run some errands or take a whole day off to go to the Venezuelan Embassy in Abu Dhabi and I've never
got a no by an answer from my manager, they all know that unplanned issues happen, but, you need to plan for the ones
you know will happen, like visa or passport renewals, medical appointments and that kind of things so your team adds some
buffer time in the sprint, accounting for your time off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being a dubizzler, also comes with some unexpected perks, as you might imagine already, my name is Israel, and it's
a FAQ in immigration all the time. So, first time I went out of the country and came back, I got a weird look from the
immigration officer and a "please, go to office number 2" as he handed me my passport back. And there I was, with a lot
of long bearded guys waiting for my turn and and Arab guy just calls my name "Israiil?" (which is Arabic for my name),
I approach the counter and the guy starts throwing Arabic to me, and I speak no Arabic, I don't know what he said, but
to me it sounded something like &lt;em&gt;hala mahala hammdulleh hamdu affek hal&lt;/em&gt; I replied with one of the few phrases I know in
Arabic &lt;em&gt;ana la atakalam al-arabiia&lt;/em&gt; which means "I don't speak Arabic", the guy laughed and continued his Arabic monologue,
I had to interrupt him by saying "No, seriously, I don't speak Arabic". So, he started making a lot of routine questions,
"what's your full name?", "where are you from?", "how long are you planning to stay in the UAE?", "how long have you been
living in the UAE?", "where do you live?", "where do you work?", and then, the surprise came. "oh! you work at dubizzle,
it's ok, it's ok, I like dubizzle very much, take you passport, khalas... go, go go... it's ok". Everytime I say I work
at dubizzle, feels like I'm a rockstar and I didn't knew about it, at each and every hackathon or conference I've been to
in the UAE, working at dubizzle inspires some kind of respect, and I'm humbled every time it happens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;A day in the life&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working at dubizzle, a platform that operates at a huge scale, presents a lot of challenges as a Software Engineer. Everything
we write and deploy to production needs to be extensively tested, it needs to scale well and have proper monitoring and
alerting in place so in case something fails, we are informed by our systems and not by the Customer Support calling the 
on-call number saying an angry user is yelling because something is not working, we have a &lt;em&gt;users comes first&lt;/em&gt; kind of principles,
so everything we do is to give more value to the users and most of out tests are to research how the users are using
our platform and see how we can deliver more value to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nowadays, we are migrating the whole platform to a microservices oriented architecture, so, most of today's challenges
are in two fronts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1.- Breaking out a legacy monolith into independent, scalable, deployable, and testable services&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2.- Building those microservices while keeping a rollback option in case of something horrible happening&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, we are not facing that dilemma of "should this be a different package?", now it's more "where should I build this?",
we try to keep our services from doing more than one thing, simplicity is the main value now, so far, we've deployed over 70
services and we continue to break the monolith into smaller units, all powered by python and django for our backends and react for
our frontend, running on top of AWS. Does this sound like a place you would like to work at? leave me a comment! and we can talk about it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Blog"></category><category term="personal"></category><category term="career"></category><category term="middle east"></category><category term="dubizzle"></category></entry><entry><title>PyCon: Challenge Accepted</title><link href="//iffm.me/pycon-challenge-accepted.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-08-01T00:00:00+04:00</published><updated>2017-08-01T00:00:00+04:00</updated><author><name>Israel Fermín Montilla</name></author><id>tag:iffm.me,2017-08-01:/pycon-challenge-accepted.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Everyone who has known me long enough, knows that I'm a huge fan of Python programming language,
for several reasons, ease of use, ease of learning, the huge amount of libraries, frameworks and
packages in general available in PyPI, it's not perfect but it has become my tool of choice …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Everyone who has known me long enough, knows that I'm a huge fan of Python programming language,
for several reasons, ease of use, ease of learning, the huge amount of libraries, frameworks and
packages in general available in PyPI, it's not perfect but it has become my tool of choice for
most of my problem solving writing software and career choice, I've been working writing python
code ever since my internship in 2011 and even organized the first and, so far, only PyCon edition
in my home country (Venezuela)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ever since I organized PyConVE 2012, I was a bit disappointed I had so much stuff to do and handle
for the conference that I didn't have time to speak myself, give a talk or a workshop at the conference
I organized, so, it was on my checklist to speak at a PyCon as a personal goal and kind of a dream,
that's the biggest Python event a local community organizes in their country so it's quite a big deal
for Pythonistas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, I applied to speak at several Pycons, first I applies to PyCon Australia, I got denied but
they provided a great feedback on how to properly write talk proposals to PyCon (thanks a lot guys!).
So, I decided to apply to PyCon Poland, PyCon Spain and PyCon South Africa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm honored and pleased that my talk &lt;strong&gt;django in the real world&lt;/strong&gt; was accepted in PyCon Poland and also
in PyCon Spain. I'm still waiting for news from South Africa. I will for sure share my experience in both
conferences, I'm so excited and thankful with my employer, dubizzle, for sponsoring my trip to the conference,
with the organizers for this huge opportunity and specially with my wife because she won't be able to go
with me and she's spending almost one week alone with our baby.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Blog"></category><category term="personal"></category><category term="speaking"></category><category term="pycon"></category></entry><entry><title>Reflexión del día que me fui del país</title><link href="//iffm.me/reflexion-del-dia-que-me-fui-del-pais.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-11-21T00:00:00+04:00</published><updated>2014-11-21T00:00:00+04:00</updated><author><name>Israel Fermín Montilla</name></author><id>tag:iffm.me,2014-11-21:/reflexion-del-dia-que-me-fui-del-pais.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Bueno, no se si estoy intenso ya con el tema de las reflexiones pero
esta será la última al menos por un buen tiempo, lo que ocurre es que
hace poco conseguí un par de escritos que pensé que había perdido cuando
formateé la computadora acá en Dubai apenas llegué …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Bueno, no se si estoy intenso ya con el tema de las reflexiones pero
esta será la última al menos por un buen tiempo, lo que ocurre es que
hace poco conseguí un par de escritos que pensé que había perdido cuando
formateé la computadora acá en Dubai apenas llegué.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Esto lo escribí el Miércoles 7 de Mayo de 2014, justo el día que estaba
emigrando.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Acá... lo que escribí&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Siempre que viajo, tengo la mala costumbre de estar hasta la noche antes
del vuelo haciendo maletas, esta vez no fue la excepción.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Terminé de arreglar las cosas a las 2:00am con mi mamá, luego de eso me
puse a ordenar un poco el closset pues es probable que mi prometida se
quede en mi habitación hasta que, finalmente, nos casemos en diciembre.
Al final terminé acostándome a las 5:00am.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;La mañana transcurrió sin mucha novedad, a las 11:00am ya estábamos
bajando al aeropuerto y ya a las 13:00 estaba chequeado y sentado
tomándome algo con mi familia, mi familia completa, la que me tocó (mi
papá, mi mamá y mi hermano) y la que yo tuve la suerte de elegir (mi
prometida y su familia).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Por recomendación de la aerolínea, debía entrar al área de embarque a
las 14:00, así que a esa hora nos dirigimos a la puerta que dirige a esa
zona, las lágrimas no se hicieron esperar, abrazos y besos para decirnos
“hasta luego” pues en diciembre estaré de vuelta.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;El camino al aeropuerto estuvo lleno de reflexiones, en una de las
cuales planteé, ¿por qué tiene que ser así?, el ideal venezolano desde
que tengo uso de razón siempre ha sido graduarse e irse del país, sea
por trabajo o a estudiar un post grado, la cosa es, no debería ser así,
¿por qué no prosperar en tu propio país?, después de todo es tu casa,
¿no?. Pues la respuesta es muy sencilla, también, desde que tengo uso de
razón, la manera de sobresalir entre los demás, no es hacer las cosas
bien necesariamente sino ser &lt;em&gt;más vivo que el de al lado&lt;/em&gt;, la
supervivencia del más vivo o, como se dice coloquialmente, &lt;em&gt;la viveza
criolla&lt;/em&gt;, ojo, no digo que todo el mundo sea así, pero una gran mayoría
piensa así, entonces, el ideal de éxito pareciera ser “quédate y trata
de ser más vivo que los demás, o vete a un país donde todo el mundo sea
honesto y haz las cosas como deben ser”, es decir, no te comas la luz,
cruza la calle por el rayado, no botes basura en la calle, no orines en
la calle ni enseñes a tu hijo a hacerlo, entre muchas otras cosas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;La verdad es que la conversación estuvo muy amena, como siempre con mi
familia, la cuestión es que tomará bastante tiempo antes de sentarnos en
la misma mesa como hoy, a disfrutar de un buen café y hablar de
cualquier cosa, pasará algo de tiempo antes de que podamos volver a
abrazarnos como hoy mientras nos despedíamos, ahora que estoy
emprendiendo camino a otras latitudes, entiendo cuando mi mamá me decía
“algún día dirás, ¿por qué no abracé más a mis padres?”, le doy toda la
razón, nunca he sido muy cariñoso porque no me criaron así, pero justo
mientras escribo este post estoy sobrevolando el océano atlántico camino
a mi primera escala, el asiento a mi lado está vacío, como también
estará vacío el asiento frente a mi en unas horas cuando me siente a
almorzar y mañana cuando me siente a desayunar, y el día siguiente, y el
siguiente... darse cuenta de esto te pega un poco y despierta la
nostalgia y, lo peor, es que es la realidad de muchas personas que han
decidido experimentar “la triste alegría de emigrar”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creo que la misma situación del país me recordó las razones por las que
los jóvenes profesionales deciden irse a probar suerte en otras
naciones: justo pasando el chequeo de migración, escucho un llamado de
la aerolínea: “pasajero de Lufthansa Israel Fermín, favor presentarse en
la puerta de embarque número 12”, pensé que estaban abordando temprano
así que me apuré a la puerta de embarque, allí me informan que una de
mis maletas fue “seleccionada para revisión” y que debía bajar al área
de equipaje para abrirla, vaciarla y examinar su contenido. Allí, un
Guardia Nacional del Comando Antidrogas era el encargado de revisar mi
maleta, a pesar de que traté de buscarle conversación no era muy
hablador, pero tampoco me trató mal ni fue mal educado, simplemente hizo
su trabajo, de manera muy ordenada (de verdad, no es sarcasmo) vació el
contenido, revisó la manera y volvió a colocar todo en su lugar. Luego
de eso, le pregunto al encargado de equipaje que me acompañó si de
verdad consiguen mucho contrabando de esa manera, la respuesta fue
afirmativa, no sólo eso, sino que “es algo de todos los días”, de hecho,
hace una semana “aprehendieron a una familia completa”, sí, “el señor,
la esposa y dos niñas menores de edad”, según el señor la mayor tendría
más o menos 5 años.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luego de la revisión de equipaje, el vuelo se retrazó unos minutos,
dándome tiempo de comer algo antes del vuelo para amortiguar, entre los
locales de comida, había una arepera que de verdad no se veía bien,
quería irme por lo más económico, y lo siguiente más económico era
Burger King, hago mi cola que cada vez se hacía más larga gracias a la
lentitud del servicio y de la única cajera que se multiplexaba en tiempo
entre la cocina y la caja. Finalmente, cuando voy a pedir, no hay
tocineta, no hay aros de cebolla, no hay... bueno, ya estamos
acostumbrados, al final pedí el combo de “Dos hamburguesas con queso”
por el cual me quedan debiendo 5 bolívares porque, de nuevo, no hay
cambio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;En la cola para retirar el pedido, de nuevo, haciéndose cada vez más
larga porque no repartían, informan que la máquina de refrescos está
dañada y que no hay refrescos y que no entregarían los pedidos hasta que
la arreglaran, allí solté mi tradicional “coño de la madre, qué peo”
(perdonen si leen y no esperan malas palabras en un blog), al final,
molesto, pido mis hamburguesas, mis papas o que me regresen mi plata,
así que me dan mis hamburguesas (frías... además de pequeñas), al
finalizar mi delicioso almuerzo (esto sí es sarcasmo), abordé el avión.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lo que más me impresionó del episodio de Burger King, no fue el hecho de
que no hubiera nada, ni el mal servicio, sino que yo era el único que
estaba molesto y que estaba reclamando algo, los demás estaban
resignados a esperar quien sabe cuánto tiempo a que arreglaran la
máquina de refrescos, les dieran hamburguesas heladas y, seguramente, un
refresco que sabe a pura soda. Esa misma actitud de “cállate que sino te
van a joder” es la que nos tiene con el agua hasta el cuello y, también,
esa actitud de “si puedo jodo al que me cae mal, me mire o me hable feo”
es la que sigue echándole agua a la piscina en la que, si seguimos como
vamos, nos ahogaremos todos, mi pregunta es, ¿hasta cuándo vamos a vivir
en la mierda?, ¿hasta cuando vamos a aceptar un “no hay” por respuesta?.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Español"></category><category term="reflexión"></category><category term="personal"></category></entry><entry><title>Algo que escribí antes de emigrar</title><link href="//iffm.me/algo-que-escribi-antes-de-emigrar.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-11-20T00:00:00+04:00</published><updated>2014-11-20T00:00:00+04:00</updated><author><name>Israel Fermín Montilla</name></author><id>tag:iffm.me,2014-11-20:/algo-que-escribi-antes-de-emigrar.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Revisando archivos viejos luego de que migré a &lt;em&gt;Linux Mint&lt;/em&gt;, conseguí
algo que escribí unos 3 días antes de emigrar, recuerdo haberme sentado
en mi escritorio, aún sin poder creer que me iba de casa, que me iba de
mi país, sintiéndome muy impotente de toda la situación que me …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Revisando archivos viejos luego de que migré a &lt;em&gt;Linux Mint&lt;/em&gt;, conseguí
algo que escribí unos 3 días antes de emigrar, recuerdo haberme sentado
en mi escritorio, aún sin poder creer que me iba de casa, que me iba de
mi país, sintiéndome muy impotente de toda la situación que me había
obligado a tomar esa decisión, como he dicho varias veces, a nadie le
gusta estar lejos de sus seres queridos. Recuerdo que encendí la
computadora, inicié &lt;em&gt;vim&lt;/em&gt; y simplemente empecé a escribir, quiero
compartir acá con ustedes lo que escribí esa noche antes de acostarme a
dormir con la ansiedad del viaje que me esperaba.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Esto fue lo que escribí&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;La verdad, es que me describo como una persona poco emotiva, quizás un
poco seca y poco sentimental. Varios de mis amigos se han ido,
familiares, incluso, están haciendo vida ya fuera del país que lo tiene
todo y al mismo tiempo no tiene nada y, en sus respectivas despedidas,
estuve siempre tranquilo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Todo cambia cuando el protagonista de la despedida es uno, me jacto de
siempre hacer valer la lógica por encima de los sentimientos al mejor
estilo vulcano pero, ante ciertas situaciones, no hay manera de evitar
que el lado humano aflore, ni Spock está excento de sucumbir ante sus
emociones de vez en cuando.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mientras preparo las maletas, pongo a punto mi bolso de mano con todos
los documentos que voy a necesitar durante el viaje de casi 24 horas, no
puedo evitar, en mi cuarto, ver todos los adornos, cosas que me han
regalado y, en mi mente, revivir esas anécdotas, ex-novias que me han
dado cosas que aún conservo, buenos amigos que me han obsequiado otras
y, lo más importante, las cosas que me ha dado mi prometida que siempre
mantengo a la vista. Historias detrás de los objetos que permanecen en
las repisas de mi habitación, inertes, testigos de cómo voy tomando
algunas que quiero llevarme y metiéndolas en mi bolso mientras, otras,
permanecerán allí, inmóviles, agarrando polvo esperando que nos veamos
de nuevo algún día.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hablar del tema con mi familia, me afecta un poco, quizás bastante. Me
voy a un lugar “no-tan-cercano”, donde hay que tomar como mínimo dos
aviones para poder llegar finalmente al destino, donde el pasaje es muy
costoso como para darse el lujo de “ir de vez en cuando a visitar” y más
aún con la situación actual de mi país. Veo a mi abuela con los ojos
aguados, tratando de no llorar, mi tía de crianza, Carmen Carrillo,
también conteniendo las lágrimas y deseándome buen viaje. Mi mamá, mi
papá y mi prometida, tratando de aprovechar al máximo estos últimos días
juntos, días en los que decidí poner de lado mis proyectos para
dedicarme a estar con mi familia y terminar ciertas diligencias para el
viaje. Días en los que me doy cuenta de los obstáculos y las trabas que
ha colocado el gobierno para restringir aún más la salida de venezolanos
a otras tierras, aún cuando sea sólo por placer, salir de Venezuela es
un privilegio y un lujo que sólo algunos pueden darse mientras vemos a
los familiares de quienes hoy detentan el poder conociendo todo el mundo
y gozando de tantas comodidades que parece absurdo, no puede haber otra
reacción más que incrementar mi alivio por salir y mi repulsión hacia
quienes han causado tanto daño.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mi nombre es Israel Fermín Montilla, tengo, a la fecha, 27 años de edad,
VENEZOLANO de nacimiento y de corazón y para el momento de escribir
esto, faltan 3 días para irme del país, en búsqueda de un mejor futuro
para mi, para mi prometida, que en diciembre será mi esposa, y para los
hijos que planeamos tener, los nietos que queremos darle a nuestros
padres. Lamentablemente, en la Venezuela actual hay pocas oportunidades
de desarrollo, la posibilidad de independizarse, salir de la casa de los
padres y tener uno su propia vivienda es casi, por no decir, totalmente,
nula. He visto a mis amigos partir, quienes me conocen saben que he
luchado hasta donde he podido, pero me apena confesar que me venció el
cansancio, ¿qué pensaría mi abuelo hoy de mi?.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;En 3 días estaré viajando a un lugar donde seré un completo extraño,
perdóname Venezuela, por dejarme vencer por el fantasma del cansancio y
dejar de nadar contra la corriente para llegar a rescatarte, espero que
todo mejore pronto y se que cuando decida volver, me recibirás con los
brazos abiertos como buena madre.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Familia, amigos, compañeros, conocidos… Hasta siempre!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-- Israel.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Español"></category><category term="reflexion"></category><category term="personal"></category></entry><entry><title>Algo hemos hecho mal en Venezuela, ¿qué?</title><link href="//iffm.me/algo-hemos-hecho-mal-en-venezuela-que.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-10-12T00:00:00+04:00</published><updated>2014-10-12T00:00:00+04:00</updated><author><name>Israel Fermín Montilla</name></author><id>tag:iffm.me,2014-10-12:/algo-hemos-hecho-mal-en-venezuela-que.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Voy ya para cinco meses viviendo fuera del país y empiezo a ver las
cosas de otra manera, quizás estando en Venezuela todo estaba tan
caótico que me impedía pensar "fuera de la caja", quizás llegó el
momento en el que dejó de importarme y me enfoqué en mis asuntos …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Voy ya para cinco meses viviendo fuera del país y empiezo a ver las
cosas de otra manera, quizás estando en Venezuela todo estaba tan
caótico que me impedía pensar "fuera de la caja", quizás llegó el
momento en el que dejó de importarme y me enfoqué en mis asuntos y en
ayudar en lo que estuviera en mis manos, lo que sí estoy seguro es que
desde afuera y conociendo otra cultura veo las cosas desde otra
perspectiva.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quizás uno ya ve todo como normal, pero, ciertamente no lo es, me
pregunto, ¿por qué?, ¿qué está mal en latinoamética?, ¿seremos los
latinos?, ¿será verdad que la culpa la tienen los españoles por mandar
puros vagos, borrachos y piratas a conquistarnos?, no lo se, lo que sí
se es que tengo demasiadas preguntas similares y dudo que pueda
responderlas todas, pero bueno, acá vamos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creo que &lt;strong&gt;todos&lt;/strong&gt; sabemos que &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_countries_by_proven_oil_reserves"&gt;Venezuela tiene una de las reservas
petroleras más grandes del
mundo&lt;/a&gt;{.reference
.external}, ¿no?, no es secreto para nadie, estamos acampando, nos
dieron ganas de ir al baño, cavamos una letrina y &lt;em&gt;BOOM&lt;/em&gt;, conseguimos
petróleo mágicamente, bueno, quizás exagero, pero estamos de primeros en
la lista, seguidos de cerca por Arabia Saudita.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No compararé Venezuela con Arabia Saudita por varias razones&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Están de segundos en el listado de países con más reservas de
    petróleo en el mundo, muy cerca de Venezuela.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Son una de las cuatro monarquías absolutas en la actualidad, con
    todos los avances en esta era moderna, considero que estan atrasados
    en lo político y lo social, o eso es lo que mi mente occidental
    piensa.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hay muchas cosas básicas que no están permitidas o están realmente
    censuradas.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Voy a comparar con los Emiratos Árabes Unidos (UAE) pues es una
experiencia que puedo contar de primera mano pues, a la fecha, llevo
casi 5 meses viviendo en Dubai.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Empecemos por las reservas petroleras, Venezuela es el primero, UAE el
séptimo, es decir, estamos, por mucho, encima de UAE en cuanto a
reservas de petróleo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;El petróleo, sigue siendo el principal combustible para &lt;strong&gt;casi todo&lt;/strong&gt;, y
sus derivados también están presentes en casi todo lo que vemos, así que
parece ser un buen negocio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Venezuela inició su carrera independentista del imperio español el 19 de
abril 1810, cuando se llevó a cabo el primer referendum de nuestra
historia, aquel en el que el Capitán General Vicente Emparam va al
balcón a preguntarle al pueblo si quieren que él siga gobernando, el
Padre José Cortés de Madariaga, chileno de nacimiento, agitaba la mano
por detrás del Capitán General, algunos dicen que estaba espantando una
mosca, otros dicen que le hacía una señal negativa al pueblo, lo cierto
es que el pueblo gritó un rotundo "NO!" y así empezó nuestra agitada
carrera hacia la independencia, la cual sellamos el 24 de junio de 1821
con la victoria de nuestro ejército patriota, Forjador de
Libertades[1], en Carabobo. O eso es lo que dicen los textos de
historia que estudié en el liceo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="La famosa escena del 19 de
abril" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/s/0rqe0kwn4yxeubp/emparan.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Por su parte, UAE logró su independencia del Reino Unido en 1971 no he
leído mucho de su historia aún, pero lo que sí se es que hasta
principios de la década de los 90, &lt;a href="http://www.forocoches.com/foro/showthread.php?t=1243603"&gt;esto era un
desierto&lt;/a&gt;{.reference
.external}, y hablo de Dubai, en 13 años levantaron rascacielos, para
2008 o 2009, ya tenían incluso islas artificiales, hoy día el edificio
más alto del mundo queda en Dubai (&lt;a href="http://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burj_Khalifa"&gt;Burj
Khalifa&lt;/a&gt;{.reference
.external}), los edificios 100% resicenciales más altos del mundo
también (&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/23_Marina"&gt;23 marina&lt;/a&gt;{.reference
.external} y &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Princess_Tower"&gt;Princess
Tower&lt;/a&gt;{.reference
.external}) e incluso uno de los hoteles más lujosos del mundo,
contruido en una isla artificial (&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burj_Al_Arab"&gt;Burj al
Arab&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Dubai en
1990" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/s/1uhz4nqv925vc0e/dubai-desierto.jpg"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Misma calle en
2003" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/s/1unk24ambjrj6tt/dubai2003.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ahora bien, todo esto fue a punta de petróleo, acá no hay bellezas ni
muchos recursos naturales, sí, hay playas muy bonitas, pero ¿montañas?,
¿nieve?, ¿picos?, ¿sabana?, pues no, acá donde no hay rascacielos y
edificios enormes, hay arena, no estoy seguro cómo obtenemos agua
potable acá porque según me han dicho, son contadas las veces que llueve
durante el año, así que no creo que haya embalses naturales como en
Venezuela, ¿turismo? hoy claro que sí, hay maravillas arquitectónicas y
de ingeniería, invirtieron sus ganancias petroleras en infraestructura,
servicios y crecimiento.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;En Venezuela, ¿qué hemos hecho con el petróleo?, desde que estudiaba
primaria, mi maestra de &lt;em&gt;sociales&lt;/em&gt; siempre decía "Venezuela es un país
monoproductor de petróleo" y eso mismo fue repetido por distintos
profesores hasta que salí de bachillerato y luego durante la
Universidad, en una que otra materia social (recuerden que estudié
Ingeniería), también, el mismo cuento y las mismas palabras. Todo, lo
que se hace en Venezuela, es también &lt;em&gt;a punta de petróleo&lt;/em&gt;, entonces,
por qué hay rascacielos, islas artificiales y autopistas de 16 canales
en Dubai, mientras que en Venezuela aún hay que pasar por carreteras de
tierra para llagar a algunos pueblos en los que llega señal celular de
Movistar, pero no una línea telefónica de tierra de CANTV, y ni hablemos
de internet de banda ancha. Mientras en un país se levantan rascacielos,
en el otro tardan &lt;strong&gt;años&lt;/strong&gt; para reparar una torre quemada de Parque
Central.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Parque central en
2004" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/s/542kzmo8bzzqox1/parque-central-quemado.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Y eso que Venezuela tiene más tiempo en el mercado petrolero que UAE,
Venezuela es uno de los países fundadores de la OPEP (Organización de
Paises Exportadores de Petróleo) en 1960, mientras que los Emiratos
Árabes, ingresaron en 1967, y en un país las escuelas parecen
universidades americanas (sí, las escuelas, colegios, liceos), y en el
otro el sistema de educación pública y gratuita a veces sufre para
iniciar el año escolar por falta de pupitres, goteras o fugas de agua en
los baños.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No comprendo, además, cómo en un país es normal ver tasas de homicidios
de 60 o 70 por semana, mientras que en el otro le roban el bolso a un
amigo en la playa (ayer) con la ropa, el celular y las llaves del
apartamento y &lt;strong&gt;todo el mundo&lt;/strong&gt; está impresionado por la noticia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cómo UAE teniendo mucho menos petróleo que Venezuela, está en el lugar
28 entre las &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.heritage.org/index/ranking"&gt;economías más estables del
mundo&lt;/a&gt;,
mientras que Venezuela aparece de cuarto si contamos de forma regresiva.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Esas son todas las preguntas que me hago, cualquiera podría decirme "el
desarrollo de un país no se mide por la cantidad de rascacielos que
tenga", es cierto, vamos a verlo por calidad de vida, en Venezuela,
ejerciendo mi profesión, mudarme de casa de mis padres, así fuera a una
habitación, era un sueño. Acá, puedo alquilar algo decente tranquilo,
hacer mercado y darme uno que otro gusto de vez en cuando, y en una
posición "de menor jerarquía" en la cadena alimenticia, en Caracas, era
&lt;em&gt;Lead developer / CTO&lt;/em&gt; de un startup de telefonía en la nube, acá soy
&lt;em&gt;Jr. Software Engineer&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No vamos a verlo por cantidad de rascacielos, vamos a verlo por cantidad
de recursos naturales, en Venezuela tenemos Petróleo, Gas, Carbón,
Aluminio (Bauxita, creo), Oro, Níquel, Cobre, Hierro, incluso creo que
Diamantes y, además Energía Hidroeléctrica según recuerdo de las clases
de Geografía del Prof. Tito Calderón.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No vamos a verlo en cantidad de rascacielos, vamos a verlo en
posibilidades de hacer turismo, y digo turismo natural: tenemos la Isla
de Margarita, donde tengo entendido que se puede hacer surf, wind surf y
kite surf y además, las playas más impresionantes que he visto se
encuentran contenidas en los más de 4mil Kilómetros de costa venezolana,
los ríos en la sabana, donde se puede hacer Kayak extremo, la Gran
Sabana, los asentamientos indígenas en Amazonas y Delta Amacuro, la
caída de agua más alta del mundo, el Salto Ángel, la Cueva del Guácharo,
tenemos sabana, desierto, playa y montaña, todo en un mismo país de poco
menás de 900 mil kilómetros cuadrados, ¿no tan grande eh? y además
suelos fértiles por todos lados.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cómo es posible que un país, mi país, teniendo todo eso esté en las
condiciones que está, que toda la población joven y profesional está
emigrando, literalmente &lt;em&gt;dejando el pelero&lt;/em&gt;. Dicen que nadie es profeta
en su tierra, mi teoría es que Arturo Uslar Pietri es el hombre que ha
estado más claro en la vida cuando escribió su artículo "Sembrar el
Petróleo", mi teoría es que en algún momento oculto de la historia, se
vino de paseo al medio oriente y, como el suelo es pura arena y es muy
difícil hacer crecer plantas, hicieron crecer edificios.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;¿Alguien me puede explicar?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="dafuq?" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/s/bkk53ile2u1jlrs/jackie-chan-meme.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] Hoy, Follador de libertades&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Español"></category><category term="reflexion"></category><category term="personal"></category></entry><entry><title>¿Y si me compro una Mac?</title><link href="//iffm.me/y-si-me-compro-una-mac.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-10-03T00:00:00+04:00</published><updated>2014-10-03T00:00:00+04:00</updated><author><name>Israel Fermín Montilla</name></author><id>tag:iffm.me,2014-10-03:/y-si-me-compro-una-mac.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Llevo ya un par de meses considerando la posibilidad, sí, YO, Israel
Fermín Montilla llevo un par de meses considerando la posibilidad de
comprarme una &lt;em&gt;MacBook&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No, no me hackearon github y subieron este artículo, tampoco estoy
sufriendo de algún tipo de enfermedad mental, mucho menos considero que
he aprendido …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Llevo ya un par de meses considerando la posibilidad, sí, YO, Israel
Fermín Montilla llevo un par de meses considerando la posibilidad de
comprarme una &lt;em&gt;MacBook&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No, no me hackearon github y subieron este artículo, tampoco estoy
sufriendo de algún tipo de enfermedad mental, mucho menos considero que
he aprendido todo lo que hay que aprender de Linux, tampoco me fastidié
de Linux, simplemente estoy considerando la posibilidad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;En Venezuela era impensable e incomprable, pero acá, es algo que puedo
hacer, podría fácilmente adquirir una MacBook Pro retina display,
instalar homebrew y usarla también como máquina de desarrollo, ¿por qué
no probar algo diferente?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Problem?" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/s/aeyb7a5txzkqw2d/thinkdifferent.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Siempre he sido un crítico de &lt;em&gt;Apple&lt;/em&gt; y de todo lo que representa,
siempre he dicho que es una fábrica de juguetes y que el único juguete
que sirve es el iPod Classic, porque es fácil de usar, cumple su
cometido muy bien y le cabe una cantidad grosera de música, el mío es de
160GB y tengo &lt;strong&gt;todos&lt;/strong&gt; mis discos allí metidos y aún le cabe más
música. También siempre me he burlado de los fanáticos de &lt;em&gt;Apple&lt;/em&gt;, les
digo &lt;em&gt;iSheeps&lt;/em&gt; porque, básicamente, así se comportan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="iSheeps en
formación" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/s/2eygv1qqyzjf7h2/isheeps.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yo no soy una oveja, creo que soy mejor que eso, pero luego, pensando al
respecto, tener una Mac, no me hace &lt;em&gt;iSheep&lt;/em&gt;, comprar todo lo que tenga
la manzana mordida y ciegamente decir que es superior aunque
técnicamente sea falso sí, al fin y al cabo, como Ingeniero y como
programador, siento que debería aunque sea probar para definir si es
bueno o malo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Algunas de las ventajas que veo respecto de tener una Mac son:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Software que funciona:&lt;/strong&gt; no es que Linux no funcione es sólo que a
    veces requiere de algunos pasos adicionales de configuración para
    que funcione como debe ser, en Mac simplemente instalas y ya, igual
    que en Windows.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sistema operativo estable:&lt;/strong&gt; no es que Linux no sea estable, es
    que Windows, la otra alternativa en cuanto a sistemas operativos
    "mainstream", no lo es tanto, acá Linux y Mac, parecieran estar a la
    par pues ambos son sistemas Un*x (o eso es lo que nos hacen creer).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Compatibilidad:&lt;/strong&gt; bueno, no es que en Linux haya problemas con
    drivers ¿verdad?, uno siempre logra hacer funcionar las cosas, a
    veces cuesta un poco más de tiempo, pero no hablemos de drivers y
    software técnico, la mayoría de los entornos de desarrollo y
    servidores de base de datos, storage no-sql, etc funcionan perfecto
    en Linux, hablemos de software para uso diario, &lt;em&gt;Skype&lt;/em&gt;, el plugin
    de &lt;em&gt;Hangouts&lt;/em&gt; para &lt;em&gt;Chrome&lt;/em&gt;, estemos claros que &lt;em&gt;LibreOffice&lt;/em&gt;
    apesta, hay muchas alternativas para producir documentos, incluso de
    mayor calidad que con &lt;em&gt;Word&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;PowerPoint&lt;/em&gt; o incluso &lt;em&gt;KeyNote&lt;/em&gt;, está
    LaTex, por ejemplo, y hay miles de librerías para producir
    presentaciones excelentes usando HTML, y JavaScript, pero muchas
    veces uno simplemente quiere hacer algo rápido, sin necesidad de
    escribir mucho código. Skype, por ejemplo, es imposible de instalar
    en &lt;em&gt;Debian&lt;/em&gt;, el paquete está corrupto, el de &lt;em&gt;Ubuntu&lt;/em&gt; y &lt;em&gt;Linux Mint&lt;/em&gt;
    funciona perfecto, lo mismo que con los plugins de &lt;em&gt;HangOuts&lt;/em&gt;,
    incluso el plugin de &lt;em&gt;Flash Player&lt;/em&gt; me ha dado problemas en &lt;em&gt;Ubuntu&lt;/em&gt;
    luego de un tiempo.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Software de grabación:&lt;/strong&gt; todos saben que toco guitarra, me
    gustaría empezar a grabar las cosas que compongo, &lt;em&gt;Audacity&lt;/em&gt; apesta
    y &lt;em&gt;Ubuntu Studio&lt;/em&gt; a veces me deja mal. He visto mucha gente trabajar
    con &lt;em&gt;Garage Band&lt;/em&gt; y hacer cosas geniales.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Esas son algunas de las razones que consigo como para una eventual
migración, según tengo entendido, son geniales como máquinas personales
y para realizar trabajos multimedia, bueno, me consta porque mi hermano
es diseñador gráfico y todo lo hace allí, igual en varios estudios de
grabación (claro, ellos usan &lt;em&gt;Pro Tools&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mi mayor preocupación al respecto es la ausencia de un gestor de
paquetes nativo, no puedo simplemente hacer &lt;em&gt;aptitude install&lt;/em&gt; y que
todo funcione de maravilla. Todos los usuarios &lt;em&gt;Mac&lt;/em&gt; en la oficina me
dicen que &lt;em&gt;homebrew&lt;/em&gt; hace el trabajo bastante bien, incluso, mi pana de
&lt;a href="http://python.org.ve"&gt;PyVE&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://github.com/satanas"&gt;Wil
Álvarez&lt;/a&gt; me dice que
es algo que vale la pena probar y que está súper feliz programando en su
&lt;em&gt;MacBook&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simplemente lo estoy considerando, necesito leer más al respecto, quizás
jugar un par de días con una a ver qué decido hacer.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Español"></category><category term="personal"></category></entry><entry><title>Ahora soy lead developer y no tengo mucha idea: anécdotas y reflexión</title><link href="//iffm.me/ahora-soy-lead-developer-y-no-tengo-mucha-idea-anecdotas-y-reflexion.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-09-23T00:00:00+04:00</published><updated>2013-09-23T00:00:00+04:00</updated><author><name>Israel Fermín Montilla</name></author><id>tag:iffm.me,2013-09-23:/ahora-soy-lead-developer-y-no-tengo-mucha-idea-anecdotas-y-reflexion.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Primero que nada, me gustaría pedir disculpas (o permiso xD) si cometo
algún error ortográfico en este artículo, se me olvidó pasar el
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://aspell.net/"&gt;aspell&lt;/a&gt;, el hecho es que,
para ponerlos un poco en contexto, vengo de un rato un poco etílico.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bueno, para empezar, quienes me conocen y están pendientes …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Primero que nada, me gustaría pedir disculpas (o permiso xD) si cometo
algún error ortográfico en este artículo, se me olvidó pasar el
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://aspell.net/"&gt;aspell&lt;/a&gt;, el hecho es que,
para ponerlos un poco en contexto, vengo de un rato un poco etílico.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bueno, para empezar, quienes me conocen y están pendientes de mi
desarrollo como profesional, saben que ahora estoy en un puesto de
&lt;em&gt;líder de proyecto&lt;/em&gt; en un startup de telefonía en la nube. Además, quien
me conozca sabe que los temas &lt;em&gt;gerenciales&lt;/em&gt; siempre me han dado ladilla,
como decimos acá en Venezuela.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;El tema es que siempre, desde que tengo personal a mi cargo, me he
esforzado en hacerles entender que &lt;strong&gt;no&lt;/strong&gt; trabajan para mi, &lt;strong&gt;sino
conmigo&lt;/strong&gt;, es decir, &lt;strong&gt;no soy&lt;/strong&gt; su jefe, sino alguien que los debe
ayudar a cumplir con sus obligaciones a tiempo y a quien le pueden
preguntar en caso de alguna duda, en fin, alguien quien puede
enseñarles, una especia de mentor o profesor o como quieran verlo. Para
mi, la definición de un líder, debe ser alguien a quien respetas
profesional y personalmente, alguien de quien consideras que puedes
aprender y a quien no le molesta aprender de ti. Eso, para mi, es un
líder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luego, está otro tema, uno que se remonta a cuando estaba estudiando en
la UCAB y discutía temas diversos con mi pana &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://gerardobarcia.com/blog/"&gt;Gerardo
Barcia&lt;/a&gt;, gran
fanático de los temas que tienen que ver con Gerencia de Proyectos. Uno
de los temas que siempre causó controversia fue el del papel del
Ingeniero en un proyecto: gerente o ejecutor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Siempre abogué por el papel del Ingeniero como &lt;em&gt;ejecutor&lt;/em&gt; de un
proyecto, es decir si estudias &lt;em&gt;supuestamente&lt;/em&gt; 5 años en una Universidad
y te enseñan a programar y diversos conceptos de sistemas operativos y
distribuidos, es para que los apliques en los sistemas que vas a
implementar o en los proyectos que vayas a desarrollar, además, en el
mundo de la informática se aplica mucho lo que yo llamo la &lt;em&gt;cultura
hacker&lt;/em&gt;, que es el hecho de &lt;em&gt;respetar&lt;/em&gt; a alguien que sabe más que tú y
que de verdad puedes comprobar que es así, es decir, alguien quien sabe
de qué habla y de quien puedes aprender o, quizás no, quizás es
simplemente alguien que está a tu mismo nivel pero que tiene las mismas
ganas que tu de aprender y tiene la misma &lt;em&gt;curiosidad científica&lt;/em&gt; por
descubrir cosas y, quizás &lt;em&gt;reinventar la rueda&lt;/em&gt; sólo para ver cómo
funciona.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Por otra parte, mi pana Gerardo siempre pensó que el rol del Ingeniero
en un proyecto es el del Gerente. Decirle a los técnicos qué hacer y
cómo hacerlo, estimar el tiempo que deberían tardarse, supervisarlos,
ver que lo que hacen cumple y aceptarlo o rechazarlo y dar directrices
de cómo y por dónde debe encaminarse el proyecto, es decir, el rol del
gerente de proyectos o, quizás, consultor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;¿Quién tenía la razón?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pues creo que ambos, un Ingeniero en un proyecto debe cumplir ambos
roles, sin embargo para poder liderar un equipo, &lt;strong&gt;siempre&lt;/strong&gt; he dicho
que debes tener experiencia suficiente como para poder decirle a alguien
lo que debe hacer con total confianza, es decir, poder tener la
habilidad, el conocimiento y la experiencia para conocer y prever
imprevistos dentro del proceso y advertir a la persona acerca de &lt;em&gt;con
qué se podría encontrar&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;El punto es que a mi pana Gerardo, le ha tocado programar, y programar
&lt;strong&gt;duro&lt;/strong&gt;, al igual que a mi. Desarrollar sistemas en los que &lt;em&gt;alguien&lt;/em&gt;
nos dice qué hacer y cuáles son las necesidades y debemos escribir
software que las cubra o que las automatice de la mejor manera posible y
sin poder tomar muchas decisiones acerca del &lt;em&gt;cómo&lt;/em&gt; implementar las
cosas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ahora a mi, aunque considero, &lt;em&gt;quizás&lt;/em&gt;, no tener la experiencia
necesaria, me toca liderar un equipo de programadores. Mi equipo me
respeta profesionalmente y nos llevamos &lt;strong&gt;muy bien&lt;/strong&gt; personalmente, de
hecho, me parece que mi equipo está conformado por las mejores personas
que alguien podría querer, todos le ponen muchísimas ganas e incluso han
resuelto problemas en los que no tenía ni idea ni tiempo de revisar a
fondo cómo solventarlos, obviamente, todos estamos aprendiendo, ellos
porque aún están estudiando en la Universidad y el trabajo les sirve de
experiencia y yo porque es mi primer trabajo al frente de un equipo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Como &lt;em&gt;persona a cargo&lt;/em&gt; de un equipo, he metido la pata y &lt;strong&gt;mucho&lt;/strong&gt;,
desde estimando tareas que toman más de lo que pensé, porque en realidad
no eran una tarea sino &lt;strong&gt;muchas&lt;/strong&gt; que eran necesarias para cumplir un
objetivo, causando que quizás la persona se frustrara porque se tardó
mucho haciéndola, hasta viendo dependencias entre tareas que eran obvias
y asignándolas de manera errada con prioridades distintas y retrasando
algunas entregas, sí, lo se, &lt;strong&gt;terrible&lt;/strong&gt;. Pero el colmo, y lo que me
hace escribir este artículo es que ocurrió algo en una reunión que me
hizo cuestionarme a mi mismo como líder de proyecto y como Ingeniero a
cargo de un proyecto:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hace más o menos un mes y medio, se discutió el flujo de un proceso y
cómo debía ser implementado yo dije que debía ser de &lt;em&gt;X&lt;/em&gt; forma y el CEO
dijo que debía ser de &lt;em&gt;Y&lt;/em&gt; forma, al final, se hizo de la forma &lt;em&gt;Y&lt;/em&gt;, pero
el tiempo demostró que la forma &lt;em&gt;X&lt;/em&gt; era la correcta, entonces, tiempo y
esfuerzo &lt;em&gt;quizás&lt;/em&gt; perdidos. No me duele mi tiempo y mi esfuerzo, sino el
de mi equipo porque fue &lt;strong&gt;mi culpa&lt;/strong&gt; que las cosas no se hicieran bien
desde el principio, no se, capaz me faltó liderazgo o capacidad de
&lt;em&gt;algo&lt;/em&gt; en el momento de la primera discusión, no lo se, el punto es que,
reflexionando, capaz producto de las bebidas espirituosas de hoy, he
empezado a pensar que quizás no estoy listo para asumir
responsabilidades de este calibre aún, quizás sea algo de actitud o
quizás sea algo de aptitud. Ustedes, ¿qué piensan?.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Español"></category><category term="reflexion"></category><category term="personal"></category></entry><entry><title>Y al fin!, me estrené como ponente</title><link href="//iffm.me/y-al-fin-me-estrene-como-ponente.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-08-10T00:00:00+04:00</published><updated>2013-08-10T00:00:00+04:00</updated><author><name>Israel Fermín Montilla</name></author><id>tag:iffm.me,2013-08-10:/y-al-fin-me-estrene-como-ponente.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Bueno, esto ya es tema viejo, pero no había tenido tiempo de escribir al
respecto. Desde que organicé el &lt;em&gt;PyConVE2012&lt;/em&gt; había tenido la idea de
probar cómo me iba dando alguna ponencia o algún tutorial, ya en la
Universidad era preparador y miembro del &lt;em&gt;Sun Team University&lt;/em&gt;, una de
las …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Bueno, esto ya es tema viejo, pero no había tenido tiempo de escribir al
respecto. Desde que organicé el &lt;em&gt;PyConVE2012&lt;/em&gt; había tenido la idea de
probar cómo me iba dando alguna ponencia o algún tutorial, ya en la
Universidad era preparador y miembro del &lt;em&gt;Sun Team University&lt;/em&gt;, una de
las iniciativas académicas de &lt;em&gt;Sun Microsystems&lt;/em&gt; que &lt;em&gt;Oracle&lt;/em&gt; mató luego
de la compra. En el &lt;em&gt;Sun Team&lt;/em&gt; daba charlas y también como preparador
hablaba en público, pero es muy diferente el ámbito académico de hablar
en una conferencia ante otros especialistas quizás con más experiencia o
mejor preparados que yo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Desafortunadamente, en el &lt;em&gt;PyCon&lt;/em&gt; sabía lo que me esperaba pues éramos
pocos organizando e iba a tener que estar corriendo de un lado a otro de
la sede (la UCAB) resolviendo problemas de última hora, así que decidí
no postular ninguna charla.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Este año, mi buen amigo &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/kadaba"&gt;Jin
Kadaba&lt;/a&gt; estaba
organizando el &lt;a href="http://flisol.org.ve"&gt;FLISOL 2013&lt;/a&gt;,
y me invitó a dar una charla. Como es una conferencia de
Software Libre y se acepta cualquier tema relacionado, decidí iniciarme
con una charla no-técnica, hablé sobre Comunidades de Software Libre y
mi experiencia en &lt;em&gt;PyVE&lt;/em&gt; y organizando el &lt;em&gt;PyCon&lt;/em&gt;. Al parecer a la gente
le gustó.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luego de un par de meses, Mimia Lo, una buena amiga de la Universidad,
estaba de nuevo organizando las
&lt;a href="http://joincic.com.ve"&gt;JOINCIC&lt;/a&gt; y me invitó a
proponer alguna charla, confieso que tengo un poco de miedo a hablar en
público, así que decidí no pararme en la tarima del Aula Magna, sino más
bien dar un taller práctico, propuse un par de mesas de trabajo a ver si
aprobaban al menos una, para mi sorpresa me pidieron dar las dos :-) y
estaba muy contento.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tanto el FLISOL como las JOINCIC fueron muy gratas experiencias para mi,
tuve la oportunidad de compartir y conocer a otras personas entusiastas
del Software Libre en el FLISOL y de compartir con viejos amigos de la
Universidad en las JOINCIC, sin mencionar que pude dar a conocer algo de
Python en ambos eventos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Acá les dejo los slides de las tres presentaciones, espero sean de su
agrado:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FLISOL&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Comunidad: orden dentro del caos, caos dentro del orden&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;a href="http://www.slideshare.net/iferminm/comunidad-caos-dentro-del-orden-orden-dentro-del-caos"&gt;http://www.slideshare.net/iferminm/comunidad-caos-dentro-del-orden-orden-dentro-del-caos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;JOINCIC&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Testing: la etapa olvidada&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;a href="http://www.slideshare.net/iferminm/testing-etapa-olvidada"&gt;http://www.slideshare.net/iferminm/testing-etapa-olvidada&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Iniciación a las artes marciales con Python&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;a href="http://www.slideshare.net/iferminm/iniciacin-a-las-artes-marciales-con-python"&gt;http://www.slideshare.net/iferminm/iniciacin-a-las-artes-marciales-con-python&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Español"></category><category term="personal"></category></entry><entry><title>Graduado, ¿y ahora?</title><link href="//iffm.me/graduado-y-ahora.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-06-27T00:00:00+04:00</published><updated>2012-06-27T00:00:00+04:00</updated><author><name>Israel Fermín Montilla</name></author><id>tag:iffm.me,2012-06-27:/graduado-y-ahora.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Bueno, vengo con otra reflexión respecto a qué ocurre al culminar la
carrera a nivel universitario, quiero empezar aclarando que acá expondré
mi (¿poca?) experiencia personal y este artículo estará marcado por mi
manera particular de ver las cosas que no necesariamente resulta ser la
de todos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Realmente no hace …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Bueno, vengo con otra reflexión respecto a qué ocurre al culminar la
carrera a nivel universitario, quiero empezar aclarando que acá expondré
mi (¿poca?) experiencia personal y este artículo estará marcado por mi
manera particular de ver las cosas que no necesariamente resulta ser la
de todos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Realmente no hace mucho que salí de la Universidad al campo laboral
formalmente, aunque durante mis años de estudiante trabajé en un par de
cosas. Parte de mi filosofía y experiencia durante la carrera ya la he
escrito en un artículo anterior, y en otro bastante reciente, sin
embargo, muchas cosas van cambiando a lo largo del tiempo, no es que sea
un profesional muy experimentado, pero, espero que estas líneas le
sirvan a alguien para guiarse, eso si, sin echarme la culpa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Particularmente, mientras estuve estudiando y trabajando, tuve un
pequeño complejo de inferioridad por no estar aún graduado, aquí en
Venezuela, como se dice en criollo, "la gente come mucho título", es
decir, sin el título no eres nadie, sin el certificado, no sabes. Ahora,
acabando de salir, el complejo es el mismo, pero por estar "recién
graduado". Esas dos etiquetas son temas sociales muy graves, he
conseguido TSU que saben mucho más que muchos Ingenieros que conozco y
estudiantes que pueden resolver un problema mejor que un profesional ya
graduado, por ello, no hay que acomplejarse por estar en alguna de esas
situaciones, al final, lo que le interesa a la empresa es alguien que
haga el trabajo y que pueda hacerlo bien, mientras, tanto las empresas
como los profesionales, no entiendan esto, el mundo laboral estará
plagado de piratas con título y gente brillante que, o bien está por
obtenerlo o, por alguna razón no les fue posible, la etiqueta de "recién
graduado", debería significar "soy joven y puedo aprender rápido,
contrátame" y no "no tengo experiencia, explótame".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Esos mismos complejos, me llevaron a aceptar trabajos con poca paga y
muchas responsabilidades, cobrar poco por desarrollar proyectos para
algunos clientes y no decir nada, ante esto, no me queda más que decir,
no se dejen explotar, sean pasantes o profesionales recién graduados, su
trabajo vale, no trabajen tiempo extra gratis, a menos que sea realmente
necesario o sea su culpa, respeten su horario de trabajo, sean los
primeros en llegar, pero también salgan a la hora, tienen familias,
amigos, novias con quienes compartir, quizás puedan dedicar parte de ese
tiempo, también, a algún pasatiempos o a desarrollar algún proyecto
personal o para algún cliente bajo la figura de "freelancer", utilicen
su trabajo como un gimnasio para poner el forma el músculo de
programación, para agarrar experiencia y conocimiento, pero no lo
apliquen sólo allí, citando a mi amigo Nhomar Hernández, "hay que
trabajar cada día como si fuera el último", pero no sólo en una cosa,
hay que diversificar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Una vez graduados, pensamos que dejaremos de estudiar pero, en realidad,
apenas empezamos, cada proyecto puede enviarnos varios meses a wikipedia
o hacernos sumergir en una serie de libros y conceptos que, si bien
puede que no sean técnicos de computación, forman parte del contexto del
sistema y debemos manejarlos, por ejemplo, durante mi breve paso por el
mundo de los ERP cuando trabajé
en &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://vauxoo.com/"&gt;Vauxoo&lt;/a&gt;, tuve que aprender
conceptos de contabilidad e inventarios, incluso características de
equipos de refrigeración para un proyecto, además de estudiar e
investigar muchísimo sobre las herramientas usadas en la empresa pues
eran nuevas para mi (Python y OpenObject, la plataforma de OpenERP). En
esta carrera, básicamente, nunca dejamos de estudiar y aprender,
actualmente, en mi actual trabajo
en &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://zava.com.ve"&gt;Zava&lt;/a&gt;, me toca investigar
sobre la cultura italiana alrededor del mundo y las tendencias actuales
de la misma, además del framework utilizado para el desarrollo del
proyecto (Django). Finalmente, recuerdo algo que me dijo un buen amigo,
Tomás Henríquez: "los primeros empleos te definen, mosca con lo que
eliges", ciertamente, los primeros empleos definen quien serás
profesionalmente, por ello, si en los primeros tres trabajos programaste
en Java o en PHP, o administraste servidores, muy probablemente para el
cuarto te busquen para hacer eso mismo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ciertamente, en el mismo orden de ideas de Tomás, "es preferible pasar 3
o 4 meses desempleado que trabajar en algo que no te gusta". El proceso
de hacer tu "plan de carrera" debe comenzar antes de graduarte, debes
pensar qué quieres hacer, en mi caso, quiero especializarme en
Desarrollo de Software, un campo muy competitivo, por ello, seleccioné
herramientas que no fueran muy comunes en el área, de esta manera te
diferencias del resto, claro que se programar en PHP y Java (en .NET no
por un tema de principios) pero todo el mundo programa en PHP, .NET y
Java, por lo que en un primer momento seleccioné Perl como el lenguaje
en el que me especializaría, empecé a hacer tutoriales, leer libros y
hacer algunos programas utilizando las librerías del CPAN, esto cambió
cuando entré en &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://vauxoo.com/"&gt;Vauxoo&lt;/a&gt; y
aprendí Python, mi actual hacha de batalla, por ahora, mi plan de
carrera es especializarme en Desarrollo Web, en todos sus campos,
Back-End y Front-End: desde servicios web y web semántica, hasta RIA, un
buen programador debe ser versátil y adaptarse a cualquier parte del
proyecto. Para cerrar, quiero aclarar que con esto último no estoy
diciendo que se casen con una tecnología o un lenguaje en particular,
aprendan de todo un poco, sean buenos, pero hay que especializarse y ser
excepcionalmente bueno en algo, yo elegí Desarrollo en Python, y estoy
trabajando en ello, también programo en PHP, Java, Perl y C/C++ si es
necesario, pero mi principal herramienta es Python y, aún así, tengo
intenciones de aprender Ruby.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Español"></category><category term="personal"></category><category term="reflexión"></category></entry><entry><title>Una nueva etapa se cierra</title><link href="//iffm.me/una-nueva-etapa-se-cierra.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-06-23T00:00:00+04:00</published><updated>2012-06-23T00:00:00+04:00</updated><author><name>Israel Fermín Montilla</name></author><id>tag:iffm.me,2012-06-23:/una-nueva-etapa-se-cierra.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;He tenido un poco abandonado el blog debido a mi trabajo especial de
grado (TEG) y a mi nuevo trabajo en Zava, pero poco a poco he ido
adelantando cosas y hoy conseguí algo de tiempo para escribir las
últimas cosas sobre las que he estado reflexionando las últimas semanas …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;He tenido un poco abandonado el blog debido a mi trabajo especial de
grado (TEG) y a mi nuevo trabajo en Zava, pero poco a poco he ido
adelantando cosas y hoy conseguí algo de tiempo para escribir las
últimas cosas sobre las que he estado reflexionando las últimas semanas
(o meses).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bien, tengo la satisfacción personal de haber desarrollado una buena
tesis, obtuve una calificación de 19 puntos con mención honorífica, al
jurado pareció haberle gustado mucho el trabajo que hice, mi tutor,
el Prof. Wilmer Pereira, también quedó muy satisfecho con el resultado,
igual que mi colaborador/asesor/amigo, el Prof. Carlos Pérez Díaz,
digamos que estoy cerrando otra etapa de mi vida con broche de oro, a
pesar de tardar más de 5 años en culminar mis estudios de Ingeniería en
Informática, estoy muy feliz con todo lo que aprendí y compartí con mis
profesores, algunos, verdaderos maestros, con mis compañeros y amigos,
especialmente
con Ronald Oribio, Khaterine Castellano, Viviana Trujillo, Gerardo Barcia y Jhonatan Trujillo.
También con todos los que les dí clases en mis días de preparador y
asistente docente: Ayleen Posadas, Karen Barreto, Héctor Sam,
Juan Perozo, Alfredo Nava, Oswaldo Bracho, muchísima gente hizo mi paso
por la universidad, una etapa muy especial, sobre todo mi
novia, Giselle Bracamonte, en mi último semestre, puede que quien esté
leyendo esto no conozca a quienes menciono, pero realmente no me
importa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ahora que cierro este ciclo, hay muchas cosas sobre las que reflexionar,
sobre todo ahora cuando tengo ya un poco más de un año trabajando,
desarrollando software, programando, diseñando/arquitectando soluciones,
investigando y, a veces, sufriendo por la falta de sueño, pero eso será
en otro artículo, en este me gustaría reconocer a aquellos profesores
que se ganaron mi respeto dentro del aula y tuve el gusto de ganarme su
amistad fuera de ella. Salimos de la universidad creyendo que lo sabemos
todo y, en realidad, lo sabemos, pero al mismo tiempo
no. Permítanme explicarme, conocemos la teoría, sabemos lo que es una
clase, un objeto, sabemos lo que son pruebas unitarias, podemos diseñar
e implementar un modelo de datos relacional, podemos, literalmente,
"echar código", pero la habilidad de "programar", se va adquiriendo con
el tiempo, de la misma manera que la habilidad de "entonar" un servidor
o una red. Acabados de salir de la universidad, únicamente, tenemos las
bases, queda de nuestra parte terminar de construir el edificio. Para
mi, los profesores quienes, realmente, me ayudaron a afianzar esas bases
fueron:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lúcia Cardoso&lt;/strong&gt; (en Sistemas de Base de Datos I y II), con ella
    aprendí que ser un Ingeniero en Informática, no es sólo programar,
    esas líneas y secuencias de instrucciones, normalmente, tienen el
    objetivo de satisfacer las necesidades de información de "alguien",
    por ello, debemos preocuparnos por cada aspecto de nuestra solución,
    desde el modelo de datos hasta la manera de presentarlos para que se
    conviertan en información. Un buen modelo de datos da un buen
    soporte a la información que manejará nuestro programa y nos
    facilitará la vida en capas superiores. Es además, una profesora muy
    exigente y tiene fama en los pasillos de ser uno de los filtros de
    la carrera, una fama muy bien ganada. Hoy, agradezco enormemente su
    nivel de exigencia.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Carlos Barroeta&lt;/strong&gt; (en Ingeniería y Desarrollo del Software), con
    él aprendí principios vitales para cualquier programador:
    especialmente "No reinventar la rueda", si hay algo ya probado y
    funciona, ¿por qué lo usarlo y ahorrarnos trabajo?. Temas como
    Patrones de Diseño, Programación Orientada a Objetos, Pruebas de
    Software, Separación por Capas y Metodologías Ágiles fueron el día a
    día en estas asignaturas. Es famoso en la Escuela por ser un
    entusiasta de las nuevas tecnologías y los Stack-Frameworks que
    facilitan la vida del desarrollador, hoy agradezco que haya puesto
    tanto empeño en explicar esos conceptos y en asegurarse de que los
    entendiera (a través de proyectos prácticos y complejas preguntas en
    los exámenes), de no haber sido así, hoy probablemente sería un
    programador terrible y sin ganas de superarse.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Darío León &lt;/strong&gt;(en Sistemas de Operación), aprendí cómo funciona a
    bajo nivel un sistema operativo. Los conceptos de Cambio de
    Contexto, Planificación de Procesos, qué hace el Kernel y cuáles son
    los componentes y servicios de un Sistema Operativo, aprendí de
    administración básica de sistemas Un*x y, creo que una de las cosas
    que hoy me quedan, aprendí a utilizar la herramienta que uso hoy
    para escribir cada línea de código que produzco: el editor vim.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rodolfo Campos &lt;/strong&gt;(en Sistemas Distribuidos), aprendí varios
    conceptos macro en cuanto a coordinación de sistemas paralelos
    (como un clúster) y distribuidos (como un grid): algoritmos de
    reloj, sincronización, elección del líder, protocolos de
    comunicación, redundancia y tolerancia a fallos. Fue una de las
    materias que más disfruté de la carrera, es realmente increíble cómo
    puede uno, como ingeniero, hacer posible que dos dispositivos en
    lugares geográficamente distintos puedan coordinar acciones para
    lograr una tarea en común y, además, que todo sea transparente para
    el usuario.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wilmer Pereira&lt;/strong&gt;, aunque nunca me dio clases formalmente, fue mi
    tutor de tesis y mentor en el área de investigación, siempre lo he
    considerado un modelo a seguir por todo el conocimiento que tiene y
    por su humildad y sencillez a la hora de hablar con un alumno o con
    cualquier otra persona, es realmente una persona brillante que a
    veces pareciera vivir en su propio mundo.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sus lecciones académicas y personales son muy valiosas, no puedo más que
decirles: MUCHAS GRACIAS!, espero llegar a ser al menos la mitad de
buenos de lo que ustedes son.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Español"></category><category term="carrera"></category><category term="personal"></category></entry><entry><title>Algo sobre Dennis Ritchie</title><link href="//iffm.me/algo-sobre-dennis-ritchie.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2011-10-18T00:00:00+04:00</published><updated>2011-10-18T00:00:00+04:00</updated><author><name>Israel Fermín Montilla</name></author><id>tag:iffm.me,2011-10-18:/algo-sobre-dennis-ritchie.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Quizás no sepas de quien se trata, es probable que hayas escuchado su
nombre alguna vez si (¿y sólo si?) estudias o estudiaste computación,
informática o alguna carrera similar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aún así, si no eres computista, seguramente utilizas algo basado en
alguno de sus trabajos, sin importar que utilices Windows, Linux …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Quizás no sepas de quien se trata, es probable que hayas escuchado su
nombre alguna vez si (¿y sólo si?) estudias o estudiaste computación,
informática o alguna carrera similar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aún así, si no eres computista, seguramente utilizas algo basado en
alguno de sus trabajos, sin importar que utilices Windows, Linux o Mac
OS, estás aprovechando algo del legado de este genio. Dennis Ritchie
falleció este 12 de octubre, a la edad de 70 años. Una semana despues de
que perdiéramos a otra mente brillante, pero del mundo de los negocios:
el Sr. Steve Jobs. Ritchie, quien era PhD en Ciencias de la Computación,
fue uno de los desarrolladores principales del sistema operativo UNIX y
el diseñador del Lenguaje de Programación C, co-autor del libro "The C
Programming Language" junto con Brian Kernighan, mejor conocido como
"The K&amp;amp;R Book", uno de los mejores textos de referencia acerca del
lenguaje. Si eres usuario de UNIX, Linux o Mac OS, estás utilizando algo
que se basa en uno de sus trabajos, de hecho, en ambos. Galardonado en
1999 con el Premio Nacional de Tecnología en los Estados Unidos, ganador
del Turing de 1983, autor de múltiples publicaciones en el campo de los
Lenguajes de Programación y las Ciencias de la Computación en general,
investigador como forma de vida, realmente hemos perdido a una de las
mentes más brillantes del siglo XX.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Español"></category><category term="reflexion"></category><category term="personal"></category><category term="Denis Ritchie"></category></entry></feed>