<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>/dev/isra/blog/* - speaking</title><link href="https://iffm.me/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://127.0.0.1:8000/feeds/speaking.tag.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://iffm.me/</id><updated>2017-09-01T00:00:00+04:00</updated><entry><title>PyConPL 2017</title><link href="https://iffm.me/pyconpl-2017.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-09-01T00:00:00+04:00</published><updated>2017-09-01T00:00:00+04:00</updated><author><name>Israel Fermín Montilla</name></author><id>tag:iffm.me,2017-09-01:/pyconpl-2017.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Two of my personal goals for this year were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1.- To speak at a local meetup here in Dubai&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2.- To speak at a bigger conference, anywhere&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to my wife, who is always supporting me much more than I support her, I could do
both, first one was at …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Two of my personal goals for this year were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1.- To speak at a local meetup here in Dubai&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2.- To speak at a bigger conference, anywhere&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to my wife, who is always supporting me much more than I support her, I could do
both, first one was at &lt;a href="https://www.meetup.com/Dubytes/"&gt;Dubytes&lt;/a&gt;, also, thanks to my colleague
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/dareenalhiyari?lang=en"&gt;Dareen Alhiyari&lt;/a&gt; who runs that meetup group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second one was at &lt;a href="https://pl.pycon.org/2017/index_en.html"&gt;PyCon Poland&lt;/a&gt;, this year (2017),
my talk &lt;a href="https://speakerdeck.com/iferminm/django-in-the-real-world"&gt;django in the real world&lt;/a&gt; was
accepted and my employer, &lt;a href="https://uae.dubizzle.com/"&gt;dubizzle&lt;/a&gt;, sponsored my trip there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My experience in Poland was great so far, the conference was at &lt;a href="http://www.hotelossa.pl/en/"&gt;huge beautiful venue&lt;/a&gt; 
one hour away from Warsaw, so I arrived one day before so I could walk around Warsaw and see some
historic and touristic places, &lt;a href="https://goo.gl/photos/pyRveSzZ6wAQQwnE6"&gt;the old town is beautiful&lt;/a&gt;,
and that was pretty much all I could see, didn't have time to do any museum before
going to &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arkadia_(shopping_mall)"&gt;Arkadia&lt;/a&gt; do to some shopping,
for my wife and my daughter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Public transportation is quite straightforward, the only issue is you have to ask people to write down
things if you ask for directions, everything is in Polish and it's not pronounced the same way as
written, with some time you get it, but I ended up asking people to write it for me the first day.
People were really helpful, every time I struggled with any of the ticket vending machines, someone
jumped in and helped, even if they didn't speak too much English, they did their best to understand
and help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I finished all my shopping and touristing by 22:30, so I headed to the hotel, which was just in front
of the airport, at the other side of Warsaw, I took the Tram, walked a bit to the main bus station
(I think) and waited for the 175 bus heading to Chopin Airport, at the station I had to use my
Latino defensive skills, some drunk guy tried to steal my wallet, I was carrying a lot of bags, I
was obviously a tourist, but you just don't try to steal something from a South American without at 
least a knife.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I arrived at the Hotel by 23:30, tired, took a bath and went to sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Getting to the conference&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I packed all my stuff, checked out from the hotel after breakfast and headed to the meeting point
at Chopin Airport, conference attendees started to crowd and I started to talk to random people, 
dubizzle asked me to recruit so, I started to try out my skills talking to people, asking what
they do with Python and speaking about what we do and how we do it at dubizzle, some people looked
excited when I talked about employment opportunities, some others not so much, apparently the hot
weather in summer is a deal breaker, the bus arrived, I checked in with the organizers and
boarded, it was a roughly 1hr trip to the venue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Conference&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Experiencing a conference as a speaker and as a normal attendee, is almost the same, as a speaker
people asks you much more questions about what you do and about what you will talk about, I spoke
to a lot of people with the intention of recruiting them, I was impressed about how well prepared
most people were, they had master degrees or pursuing PhD studies, academic titles mean nothing nowadays,
but they do tell you that the person takes care and time on improving himself and gaining more knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was very well organized, and there was always someone from the organizing team available to help
and to answer questions. People were also impressed about the fact that I went all the way from Dubai
to speak at their conference, I was humbled and honored to be there to be honest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the conference I was more into talking to people, I did attend to some talks, but my main
focus was networking and getting people into applying to work at dubizzle or sending me their CV.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My Talk&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'd say it was great, I got a lot of questions, which is a good sign, if you get no questions it means
that people were either not listening or did not understand a single word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm waiting for them to upload the videos from the talks to watch how I really did and some other talks
I was interested in but couldn't attend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really liked the experience, I would definitely encourage everyone to apply to speak at this kind of
conferences, I'll apply to speak at PyConPL next year for sure and will take my family as well, Warsaw
is a beautiful city, full of history and nice people. Will come back for sure!.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, if you're looking for a job and would like to relocate to Dubai, have a look &lt;a href="http://blog.dubizzle.com/uae/job-vacancies/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
at the open positions and leave me a comment, we can talk about it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Blog"></category><category term="personal"></category><category term="speaking"></category><category term="pycon"></category></entry><entry><title>PyCon: Challenge Accepted</title><link href="https://iffm.me/pycon-challenge-accepted.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-08-01T00:00:00+04:00</published><updated>2017-08-01T00:00:00+04:00</updated><author><name>Israel Fermín Montilla</name></author><id>tag:iffm.me,2017-08-01:/pycon-challenge-accepted.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Everyone who has known me long enough, knows that I'm a huge fan of Python programming language,
for several reasons, ease of use, ease of learning, the huge amount of libraries, frameworks and
packages in general available in PyPI, it's not perfect but it has become my tool of choice …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Everyone who has known me long enough, knows that I'm a huge fan of Python programming language,
for several reasons, ease of use, ease of learning, the huge amount of libraries, frameworks and
packages in general available in PyPI, it's not perfect but it has become my tool of choice for
most of my problem solving writing software and career choice, I've been working writing python
code ever since my internship in 2011 and even organized the first and, so far, only PyCon edition
in my home country (Venezuela)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ever since I organized PyConVE 2012, I was a bit disappointed I had so much stuff to do and handle
for the conference that I didn't have time to speak myself, give a talk or a workshop at the conference
I organized, so, it was on my checklist to speak at a PyCon as a personal goal and kind of a dream,
that's the biggest Python event a local community organizes in their country so it's quite a big deal
for Pythonistas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, I applied to speak at several Pycons, first I applies to PyCon Australia, I got denied but
they provided a great feedback on how to properly write talk proposals to PyCon (thanks a lot guys!).
So, I decided to apply to PyCon Poland, PyCon Spain and PyCon South Africa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm honored and pleased that my talk &lt;strong&gt;django in the real world&lt;/strong&gt; was accepted in PyCon Poland and also
in PyCon Spain. I'm still waiting for news from South Africa. I will for sure share my experience in both
conferences, I'm so excited and thankful with my employer, dubizzle, for sponsoring my trip to the conference,
with the organizers for this huge opportunity and specially with my wife because she won't be able to go
with me and she's spending almost one week alone with our baby.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Blog"></category><category term="personal"></category><category term="speaking"></category><category term="pycon"></category></entry></feed>